<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <authority state="Alabama">
        <history>
            <h2>Alabama</h2>
            <div class="byline"> Written by Daniel S. Dupre <br/>
                University of North Carolina Charlotte </div>
            <p>Alabama, originally part of Mississippi Territory, became a separate territory in 1817. The formation of Alabama Territory was strongly influenced by a group of Georgia politicians aligned with William Crawford. This Georgia faction, or "Broad River" group, was led by two of Georgia's senators, Charles Tait and William Wyatt Bibb. Both moved west to Alabama where they and other elite Georgians came to be known as the “Royal Party.” Bibb was appointed the first and only territorial governor by President James Madison. The territory's General Assembly, a bicameral body, was relatively weak compared to the governor, as was the case in most federal territories.</p>
            <p>In July, 1819 forty-four delegates met in Huntsville to write Alabama’s Constitution to prepare for statehood. They created a bicameral General Assembly divided into a Senate and a House of Representatives. Members of the House served one year terms while members of the Senate served three years. The Governor served two-year terms and was limited to two terms in office. Both members of the General Assembly and the Governor were popularly elected by ballot. The suffrage was restricted to white men over the age of 21 who had resided in the state for at least one year, but there were no property requirements. </p>
            <p>The voters of Alabama elected William Wyatt Bibb the first governor of the state where he encountered a more powerful General Assembly than he had been accustomed to in the territorial period. Legislators elected all of the heads of executive departments and they could override gubernatorial vetoes with a simple majority vote.</p>
            <p>Formal partisan divisions played almost no role in Alabama's early political history. Because the territory and state were formed during the Era of Good Feelings after the collapse of the Federalist Party through much of the country, most of Alabama’s political leaders and voters claimed allegiance to the Republican majority. Factions in Alabama formed around the Royal Party, the elite settlers with roots in the Broad River region of Georgia, and the politicians who opposed them. Because many of the leaders aligned with the Royal Party were involved in banking in Alabama, the financial collapse associated with the Panic of 1819 sharpened political conflict and gave ammunition to their more populist-oriented opponents. Regional divisions also shaped Alabama’s factionalism, especially as politicians fought over the location of the new state capital. The territorial assembly favored Tuscaloosa, a site far enough north to make it accessible to the residents of the Tennessee Valley. William Wyatt Bibb chose Cahawba instead, a site more closely situated to his political base in central Alabama. The new state assembly accepted that decision but also granted the General Assembly power to select a permanent capital in 1825 without input from the governor. At that time the seat of government shifted to Tuscaloosa, where it remained until moving to Montgomery in the 1840s.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography and Related Sources</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://www.legislature.state.al.us/misc/history/history.html">Alabama Legislative History</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://www.archives.state.al.us/aaa.html">Alabama Department of Archives and History</a>
                </li>
                <li>Atkins, Leah Rawls, Wayne Flynt, William Warren Rogers, and David Ward. <title>Alabama: The History of a Deep South State</title></li>
                <li>Dupre, Daniel S. <em>Transforming the Cotton Frontier: Madison County, Alabama, 1800-1840. <title></title></em>Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1997.</li>
                <li>Owen Thomas M. <title></title><em>History of Alabama and Dictionary of Alabama Biography 4 vols. </em>1921.</li>
                <li>Peirce, Neal R. <title></title><em>The Deep South States of America: People, Politics, and Power in the Seven Deep South States </em>(1974). Information on politics and economics 1960–72.</li>
                <li>Rogers, William Warren, et al., eds. <title></title><em> Alabama: The History of a Deep South State.</em> Tuscaloosa: The University of Alabama Press, 1994.</li>
                <li>Thorton, J. Mills, III. <title></title><em>Politics and Power in a Slave Society. </em>Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1978.</li>
                <li>Webb, Samuel L. and Margaret E. Armbrester, eds. <title>Alabama Governors: A Political History of the State.</title>Tuscaloosa: The University of Alabama Press, 2001.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Arkansas">
        <history>
            <div class="byline"> Written by S. Charles Bolton<br/>
                University of Arkansas at Little Rock </div>
            <p>By legislation enacted on March 2, 1819, Congress created Arkansas Territory out of the southern portion of Missouri Territory and declared its political life to begin on July 4 of that year. Seventeen years later, on June 15, 1836, Arkansas became a state.</p>
            <p>The government of Arkansas Territory was modeled on that of Missouri Territory as defined in an act of June 4, 1812. Executive authority was in the hands of a governor appointed by the president for a term of three years and a secretary appointed for four years who would serve in the absence of the governor. The governor and the three appointed members of the territorial superior court were empowered to make laws until a majority of the freeholders indicated that they wished to have a representative government. After that there would be a General Assembly consisting of a House of Representatives elected by free, white, male citizens twenty-one years of age or older who had been residents for at least a year and paid county or territorial taxes. Nine members of the House of Representatives were to be elected for two-year terms, and the number could increase only after there were 5,000 eligible voters in the territory. Under the act of 1812, nine members of a legislative
                council were appointed by the president out of a group of eighteen nominated by the House of Representatives, but this provision was modified by an 1816 amendment that allowed Missouri voters to elect one member of the council from each county. Any eligible voter could be elected to the House of Representatives, but members of the legislative council were required to own 200 acres of land. Arkansas could also elect a nonvoting delegate to the U.S. Congress under the same conditions as other territories.</p>
            <p>For most of the first decade, the political leaders of the territory were newcomers who came with political offices or in the hope of gaining them. The first governor, James Miller of New Hampshire, was a hero of the War of 1812, and the first secretary, Robert Crittenden of Kentucky, was a brother of the senator John J. Crittenden. The first delegate to Congress, James Woodson Bates, was a brother of Frederick Bates, secretary of Missouri Territory, and the second, Henry W. Conway, originally from Tennessee, came to the territory from Missouri with an appointment as receiver of public monies and was related to William Rector, surveyor general of Missouri, who sent a number of his family members to Arkansas as deputy surveyors.</p>
            <p>Secretary Crittenden was the political leader of Arkansas in this early period. Governor Miller did not arrive in the territory until December 1819, and by that time Crittenden had created and filled a number of offices, moved Arkansas into the second stage of territorial government, and held elections. Miller was a capable executive, but he took little interest in politics and was out of Arkansas during the four years before he resigned. His successor, George Izard of South Carolina, a general in the War of 1812, was more involved in local affairs, but Crittenden continued to exert great influence.</p>
            <p>Crittenden appears to have supported Bates in the election of 1819, and he won a plurality of the votes. Stephen F. Austin, who was in Arkansas only temporarily and did not campaign, came in second, and four other candidates, including several long-term settlers, were well back. In 1821 Matthew Lyon, who, as a Jeffersonian Democrat member of the U.S. House of Representatives several decades earlier, had been a bitter opponent of the Federalists and was convicted under the Sedition Act, ran against Bates and lost by 61 of the 2,101 votes cast. Bates did not run in 1823, and Henry W. Conway won 59 percent of the vote against Major William Bradford, who had commanded the Army post at Fort Smith from 1817 to 1822. Bates tried again in 1825, but now without the support of Crittenden, and was trounced by Conway, who took 80 percent of the vote.</p>
            <p>The election of 1827 was a turning point in Arkansas politics. Crittenden turned against Conway, who by this time was the leader of his own political faction made of relatives and friends, and backed Robert Oden. During the campaign Oden's supporters claimed that Conway had misused public funds, and Crittenden publicly attested to the validity of the charge. Conway won the election but then challenged Crittenden to a duel and received a mortal wound in the encounter. Ambrose H. Sevier, Conway's cousin and a grandnephew of John Sevier, the famous Indian fighter and Tennessee politician, won a special election that followed Conway's death.</p>
            <p>That same year Sevier married the daughter of Benjamin Johnson, a member of the superior court of the territory and the brother of Richard M. Johnson, later Van Buren's vice president. Under the leadership of Sevier, William Woodruff (the editor of the Arkansas Gazette), and Chester Ashley (a highly successful lawyer and land speculator), the Conways, the Rectors, and the Johnsons dominated Arkansas politics down to the 1850s, functioning as the Arkansas wing of the Jacksonian Democratic Party but known locally as "The Family." Among its leaders (in addition to Sevier, who served several terms in the U.S. Senate) were Governor James Sevier Conway, Governor Elias Nelson Conway, and Senator Robert Ward Johnson. A Whig Party emerged and ran spirited campaigns, but Arkansas remained solidly Democratic down to the Civil War.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Bolton, Charles S. <title>Territorial Ambition: Land and Society in Arkansas, 1800—1840.</title> Fayetteville: University of Arkansas Press, 1993.</li>
                <li>McNeilly, Donald. <title>The Old South Frontier: Cotton Plantations and the Formation of Arkansas Society, 1819—1861.</title> Fayetteville: University of Arkansas Press, 2000.</li>
                <li>Smith, Margaret Ross. <title>Arkansas Gazette: The Early Years, 1819—1866.</title> Little Rock: Arkansas Gazette Foundation, 1969.</li>
                <li>White, Lonnie J.. <title>Politics on the Southwestern Frontier: Arkansas Territory.</title> Memphis, TN: Memphis State University Press, 1964.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Connecticut">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Matthew Warshauer <br/>
                Central Connecticut State University
            </div>
            <p>As one of the original thirteen colonies, Connecticut holds a unique place in the history of democratic government in what became the United States of America. The Puritan Congregationalists who settled New England were well known for their town meetings and representative government. The Fundamental Orders, which formed the first written system of government in Connecticut, were formulated in 1639 by representatives from the towns of Hartford, Wethersfield, and Windsor. The Orders provided for the creation of a single legislative body known as the General Assembly and outlined the process for the election of magistrates. Of those magistrates, one was elected to serve for a single year as a fairly weak governor, and serving consecutive terms was prohibited. All freemen within the colony had the right to vote in these elections, and paper ballots were used in town meetings to determine the outcome. The Reverend Thomas Hooker presaged the representative nature of the Fundamental Orders by preaching a sermon in which he noted that "the foundation of authority is laid in the free consent of the people." The Fundamental Orders are the reason why Connecticut is known today as the Constitution State.</p>
            <p>The Fundamental Orders were replaced by the colonial charter of 1662; that charter continued to follow the essential character of the Orders. After the Revolution, only Connecticut and Rhode Island continued to operate under their colonial charters. Until a formal state constitution was created in 1818, Connecticut government operated on the basis of the Fundamental Orders. Some things did, however, change in the years during which the charter was in operation. In 1698 the General Assembly was divided into two houses and was composed of 200 representatives, one or two from each of the towns. Elections were held semi-annually in the April and September freemen’s meetings. Any freeman could run for office.</p>
            <p>Even though the state government was seemingly democratic in nature, the aristocracy controlled most matters. The colonial charter had created a council of twelve assistants, which served as the upper house of the Assembly, and it retained tight control over governmental matters. As historians have noted, "Its supremacy derived from the continuity of its members in office and the veto they exercised over most of the General Assembly's actions."</p>
            <p>Historian Richard Purcell notes that from 1775 to 1818, Connecticut was a state in transition: "The result was the bloodless Revolution of 1818, which gave the state a constitution as democratic as any then in existence." In the midst of these years, the nation witnessed not only a new system of government, with the ratification of the U.S. Constitution in 1789, but also the rise of a fierce two-party system of Federalists and Republicans, who did battle over what they perceived to by the proper political and economic direction of government. Connecticut became a staunchly Federalist state. Until 1819, every senator and congressman sent to the national Congress belonged to the Federalist Party, and until 1818, every seat in the upper house of the Connecticut Assembly was Federalist. It was not until 1817, with the election of Oliver Wolcott, Jr., that a Republican managed to take control of the governor's office.</p>
            <p>The Federalist Party was marked by the more traditional notion of deferential, and aristocratic, beliefs in government. It was assumed that only men of higher standing were fit for office and should control the affairs of government. Federalists feared the "mob" of democracy, which they associated with the rise of Jefferson's Republican Party. Federalists were so firmly entrenched within Connecticut that it was particularly difficult for the Jeffersonians to work their way into the state. Yearly elections took place, but the nominating system was skillfully controlled by the Federalists, who possessed an almost machine-like domination. By 1801 they had passed a "stand up" law, which replaced the written ballots cast in the freemen's meetings with a requirement to raise one's hand or stand up to show a vote. Like other forms of voice voting, this effectively stymied opposition by engendering fear of retribution.</p>
            <p>Even as the Republican Party continued to grow and spread throughout the South and Middle Atlantic region, New England—and Connecticut along with it remained almost exclusively Federalist. By 1800, with Jefferson taking over in what many termed a revolution, Federalists clung to power and fought any reforms that might allow broader democracy, and with it the Republican Party, into the state. Still, murmurings continued to grow over the inequity of taxes, the unfair apportionment of seats in the state government, certain election laws, and legislation that favored the Congregational Church, which was supported by tax money. The murmurings grew to open revolt by the second decade of the 1800s, in part because of the Federalist opposition to the War of 1812 and because of the infamous Hartford Convention. The result was the new constitution of 1818. This was the very wedge needed to allow the Democratic-Republicans to compete in the state. Even with that party's entrance, however, the going was slow. The state continued to exhibit its generally more aristocratic leanings and was decidedly against the election of Andrew Jackson to the presidency in 1824 and 1828. Even though Gideon Wells had by 1820 established a nascent Democratic Party in Connecticut, Jackson's party and administration did little to attract votes in Connecticut, or in New England more broadly. The Democratic Party viewed Connecticut as populated by opponents and as falling far more in line with the newly developed Whig Party. Indeed, it was not until the mid-1830s to 1840s, well into the evolution of the second American party system, that Democrats managed to compete with Whigs within the state.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Buell, Richard, Jr. and George J. Willauer. <title>Original Discontents: Commentaries on the Creation of Connecticut's Constitution of 1818.</title> Hamden, CT: The Acorn Club, 2007.</li>
                <li>Morse, Jarvis Means. <title>A Neglected Period of Connecticut's History, 1818–1850.</title> New York: Octagon Books, 1978</li>
                <li>Purcell, Richard J. <title>Connecticut in Transition: 1775–1818.</title> Middletown: Wesleyan University Press, 1963.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Delaware">
        <div class="byline">
            Written by Philip Lampi
        </div>
        <history>
            <p>On December 7, 1787 the Delaware State Legislature, by a unanimous vote of 30 to 0, became the first state to ratify the newly proposed national Constitution.</p>
            <p>When a new State Constitution was adopted in 1792, the office of State Executive, which had previously been called President and chosen by the Legislature, was changed to Governor, and became an elected position. The term of office was kept at three years.</p>
            <p>Delaware with only three counties (New Castle, Kent and Sussex) had the fewest in the nation. They also had the smallest State Legislature, comprised of nine State Senators and twenty-one Representatives.</p>
            <p>Each county had three Senators, serving for three years. Their terms were staggered, so that one Senator was elected every year from each county. The House of Representatives had twenty one members, seven from each county, and who were elected annually at large.</p>
            <p>Congressional, State and County Elections were held simultaneously in early October.  Delaware elected one Congressman from 1788 – 1810, two for 1812 – 1820, and then one again from 1822 onward. State offices elected by popular vote were Governor, State Senator and Representatives. County officials elected by popular vote were Levy Court Commissioners, Coroners and Sheriff.</p>
            <p>The voting alignment of the three counties, with New Castle voting Republican and Sussex and Kent being Federalist, meant that the State Legislature was almost always controlled by Federalists. As a result, from 1792 to 1820 Delaware chose Federalist Presidential Electors, even in 1820 when all four electors gave their Vice Presidential votes to Daniel Rodney, a Federalist and former Governor.</p>
            <p>The Legislature also selected United States Senators, and with the exception of Caesar A. Rodney, who was elected in 1822, all those chosen during this time period were Federalists.</p>
            <p>Party competition began with the state elections of 1792 and continued virtually unabated until 1826, when the last Federalist Governor was elected. Despite the dominance of Federalists in the Legislature, the parties were fairly balanced in popular voting strength, with Republicans electing their candidate for Governor in 1801, 1810, 1820 and 1822 and Congressmen in 1792, 1794, 1802 and capturing one of their two seats in 1816, 1818 and 1820.</p>
            <p>Delaware counties were broken down into Hundreds, which seem to be the equivalent of townships. By 1811 state election returns started to be reported by Hundreds, a procedure which began showing the tight cohesion in voting amongst Federalist and Republican tickets.</p>
            <p>The Hundreds also elected local officials such as Assessors, Inspectors and Road Commissioners. These elections were held in September, before the state voted in October, and on occasion, if they were favorable to either party, these returns were reported in the newspapers.</p>
            <p>Delaware, the first state in the Union was the last to elect a Federalist Governor.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://portal.delaware.gov/facts/history/delhist.shtml">The State of Delaware: The official website for the First State</a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Electoral College">
        <history>      
            <p>Article II, Section 1 of the Constitution of the United States reads: "The executive Power shall be vested in a President of the United States of America. He shall hold his Office during the Term of four Years, and, together with the Vice President, chosen for the same Term, be elected, as follows 
                Each State shall appoint, in such Manner as the Legislature thereof may direct, a Number of Electors, equal to the whole Number of Senators and Representatives to which the State may be entitled in the Congress: but no Senator or Representative, or Person holding an Office of Trust or Profit under the United States, shall be appointed an Elector."</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Pasley, Jeffrey L.<title>The first presidential contest: 1796 and the founding of American democracy.</title> Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 2013.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Florida">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
            Excerpt from the Florida Cultural, Historical and Information Programs Website
        </div>  
            <p>Britain gained control of Florida in 1763 in exchange for Havana, Cuba, which the British had captured from Spain during the Seven Years’ War (1756–63). Spain evacuated Florida after the exchange, leaving the province virtually empty. At that time, St. Augustine was still a garrison community with fewer than five hundred houses, and Pensacola also was a small military town.</p>
            <p>The British had ambitious plans for Florida. First, it was split into two parts: East Florida, with its capital at St. Augustine; and West Florida, with its seat at Pensacola.</p>  
            <p>The two Floridas remained loyal to Great Britain throughout the War for American Independence (1776–83). However, Spain—participating indirectly in the war as an ally of France—captured Pensacola from the British in 1781. In 1784 it regained control of the rest of Florida as part of the peace treaty that ended the American Revolution.</p>  
            <p>When the British evacuated Florida, Spanish colonists as well as settlers from the newly formed United States came pouring in. Many of the new residents were lured by favorable Spanish terms for acquiring property, called land grants. Others who came were escaped slaves, trying to reach a place where their U.S. masters had no authority and effectively could not reach them. Instead of becoming more Spanish, the two Floridas increasingly became more "American." Finally, after several official and unofficial U.S. military expeditions into the territory, Spain formally ceded Florida to the United States in 1821, according to terms of the Adams-Onís Treaty.</p>
            <p>Andrew Jackson returned to Florida in 1821 to establish a new territorial government on behalf of the United States. What the U.S. inherited was a wilderness sparsely dotted with settlements of native Indian people, African Americans, and Spaniards.</p>
            <p>As a territory of the United States, Florida was particularly attractive to people from the older Southern plantation areas of Virginia, the Carolinas, and Georgia, who arrived in considerable numbers. After territorial status was granted, the two Floridas were merged into one entity with a new capital city in Tallahassee. Established in 1824, Tallahassee was chosen because it was halfway between the existing governmental centers of St. Augustine and Pensacola.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.flheritage.com/facts/history/summary/">Florida Cultural, Historical and Information Programs
                    “A Brief History of Florida: From the Stone Age to the Space Age”
                </a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Georgia">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
            Written by Anthony Gene Carey<br/>
            Auburn University
        </div>       
            <p>Georgia entered the Union on January 2, 1788, the fourth of the original thirteen colonies to ratify the United States Constitution. The Georgia constitution of 1789 created a bicameral legislature consisting of a Senate and a House of Representatives; representatives were elected annually, senators every third year. Although Georgia's early constitutions specified neither the sex nor the race of voters, in practice eligible voters consisted of free men (predominantly whites) at least 21 years old who had paid taxes during the previous year and had resided in the county for at least six months. Each county elected one senator, and counties elected from two to five representatives, depending roughly on relative population. The legislature elected the governor to a two-year term, initially through a cumbersome process but, after a 1795 amendment, through a simple joint ballot of the legislature. Another 1795 amendment made Senate elections annual. All elections were by ballot.</p>
            <p>The 1798 constitution (frequently amended but not entirely replaced until 1861) left the basic electoral structure intact. The most important change specified the use of the "three-fifths" or "federal" ratio, which counted three-fifths of the enslaved population in addition to the free white population in apportioning seats in the state House of Representatives. The 1798 document also required regular reapportionment among counties as the population changed. The legislature continued to elect the governor until an amendment in 1824 required direct popular election of the state's chief executive. The first popular election for governor occurred in 1825. In elections for the U.S. Congress, the legislature elected senators by joint ballot, and the state alternated between a district system and a general ticket system for the direct popular election of members of the U.S. House of Representatives.</p>
            <p>Early Georgia politics was highly personal and factional. The absence of statewide elections, except for Congress, tended to localize politics and deter the formation of broad, institutionalized parties. The Federalists had some strength through the turn of the century, especially in Savannah and Augusta, but Georgia was largely a Republican state. The major political contests featured clashes among those who claimed to be Jeffersonian Republicans. Outrage over the Yazoo land frauds helped James Jackson dominate state politics for many years until his death in 1806, and William Crawford and George M. Troup then assumed the leadership of the Jackson group. John Clark headed the major rival faction. In broad terms, Jackson-Crawford-Troup adherents tended to have Virginia ties and to be based in the wealthier sections of the eastern black belt and low country. The Clark faction contained more people of North Carolina extraction and found its strongest support in frontier areas. Clark defeated Troup for the governorship in both 1819 and 1821, before Troup bested his rival in 1825. William Crawford was a major presidential contender in 1824. Excitement over these races, indeed, helped push through the amendment calling for popular election of the governor and a law mandating popular election of presidential electors. The most persistent and pressing issue of this early period was the state's efforts to push back the Creek and Cherokee nations and open Native American lands to white settlement. The short-staple cotton boom and the Panic of 1819 fueled economic and land concerns. The election returns presented in this series end just before the Georgia factions began to organize themselves into bona fide political parties that would become the Democratic and Whig parties in the state.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <title></title>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Carey, Anthony Gene. <title>Parties, Slavery, and the Union in Antebellum Georgia.</title> Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1997.</li>
                <li>Coleman, Kenneth R., gen. ed. <title>A History of Georgia, 2nd ed.</title> Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1991.</li>
                <li>Cook, James F. <title>The Governors of Georgia, 1754—2004, 3rd ed.</title> Macon, GA: Mercer University Press, 2005.</li>
                <li>Carl Vinson Institute of Government, University of Georgia <a href="http://www.cviog.uga.edu/Projects/gainfo/gacontoc.htm">Georgia Constitution Web Page</a></li>
                <li>Lamplugh, George R. <title>Politics on the Periphery: Factions and Parties in Georgia, 1783—1806.</title> Newark: University of Delaware Press, 1986.</li>
                <li>Phillips, Ulrich B. <title>Georgia and State Rights.</title> Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1902.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Illinois">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Brianne E. Peck<br/>
                Chicago History Museum
            </div>      
            <p>In 1778 American revolutionary George Rogers Clark, defending colonial interests in the Northwest, claimed the sparsely populated Illinois country for Virginia. Following the American Revolution, Illinois fell within the boundaries of the Northwest Territory and operated under the Northwest Ordinance of 1787.</p>
            <p>Settlement in this region increased, and on March 1, 1809, Illinois Territory was officially established with its capital at Kaskaskia. This sparked a wave of settlement, with most migrants hailing from the southern United States. Their influence was immediate and lasting. Not only would the territorial government select its laws from among the existing laws of the southern states, but the southern heritage of territorial residents would affect the slavery debate and political climate for decades.</p>
            <p>Under the Northwest Ordinance, the vote was restricted to property owners, but because few property owners with substantial land claims resided in Illinois Territory, a referendum was soon adopted granting suffrage to all white taxpaying males who had lived in the territory for at least one year. In October 1812, members of the first legislature, as well as the first territorial representative to the United States Congress, Shadrach Bond, were elected by popular vote.</p>
            <p>On December 3, 1818, after exaggerating population totals, Illinois became the twenty-first state admitted to the Union. The capital first remained at Kaskaskia, but it moved to Vandalia in 1819 and to Springfield in 1837. As a state, Illinois adopted a constitution that defined three branches of government marked by a strong bicameral legislature known as the General Assembly. This body, composed of the Senate and House of Representatives, met biennially. Members of the House were elected annually for each assembly. Senators served four-year terms, with half of the legislative body elected every two years. The General Assembly had the power to impeach, counted gubernatorial votes, appointed many state and local officials, and elected the four state supreme court justices, who made up the early judiciary.</p>
            <p>The governor was elected biennially by popular vote, but the powers of this office were limited. Under the constitution of 1818, the governor possessed the power of veto only as a single vote in the Council of Revision, a separate body that consisted of the governor and the justices on the state supreme court; the Council was usually neutralized by the overarching powers of the General Assembly. The governor would not gain sole power of the veto until 1848.</p>
            <p>The Illinois constitution of 1818 also gave the vote to white male inhabitants over twenty-one who had resided in the state for six months. In the early years of state government, debate surrounded the general election process. In 1819 and 1823, provisions were made for voting to take place via ballot, whereas in 1821 and 1829, viva voce voting was implemented. Viva voce eventually disappeared as population and polling places increased. </p>
            <p>Prior to 1830, local factions dominated Illinois party politics. The Harrison faction and the anti-Harrison, or Edgar-Morrison, faction were both pro-slavery but differed in approach. The Edwards and anti-Edwards factions, which sparred over patronage and the judiciary, soon replaced the Harrison factions. When anti-slavery Governor Edward Coles was elected in 1822, a fierce debate began, which gave rise to the Jacksonian politicians who would dominate Illinois politics in the ensuing years.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Alvord, Clarence Walworth. <title>The Illinois Country: 1673–1818.</title> Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1987. Originally published as Volume 1 of the Centennial History of Illinois by the Illinois Centennial Commission, 1920.</li>
                <li>Biles, Roger. <title>Illinois: A History of the Land and Its People.</title> Dekalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 2005.</li>
                <li>Boggess, Arthur Clinton. <title>The Settlement of Illinois, 1778–1830.</title> Chicago: The Chicago Historical Society, 1908.</li>
                <li>Buck, Solon J. <title>Illinois in 1818.</title> Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1967.</li>
                <li>Davis, James E. <title>Frontier Illinois.</title> Indianapolis: Indiana University Press, 1998.</li>
                <li>Leichtle, Kurt E. <title>"The Rise of Jacksonian Politics in Illinois."</title> Illinois Historical Journal, 82 (Summer 1989): 93–107.</li>
                <li>Pease, Theodore Calvin. <title>The Frontier State: 1818–1848.</title> Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1987. Originally published as Volume 2 of the Centennial History of Illinois by the Illinois Centennial Commission, 1918.</li>
                <li>Pease, Theodore Calvin and Marguerite Jenison Pease. <title>George Rogers Clark and the Revolution in Illinois: 1763–1787.</title> Springfield: The Illinois State Historical Library and The Illinois State Historical Society, 1929.</li> 
                <li>Simeone, James. <title>Democracy and Slavery in Frontier Illinois: The Bottomland Republic.</title> Dekalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 2000.</li>    
                <li>Sorensen, Mark W. "The Illinois History Resource Page." Illinois State Historical Society, December 12, 1995.<a href="http://www.historyillinois.org/Links/Illinois_History_Resource_Page/illinois_histoy_resource_page.htm.">"The Illinois History Resource Page."</a> </li>
                <li>Sutton, Robert M. <title>"Edward Coles and the Constitutional Crises in Illinois, 1822–1824."</title> Illinois Historical Journal, 82 (Spring 1989): 36–46.</li>
                <li>Sutton, Robert P., ed. <title>The Prairie State: A Documentary History of Illinois, Colonial Years to 1860.</title> Grand Rapids: William B. Eerdmans, 1976.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Indiana">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Richard F. Nation<br/>
                Eastern Michigan University
            </div>
            <p>Indiana was originally part of the Northwest Territory, established under the Ordinance of 1787. In the earliest stage of the Northwest Territory, most of the European Americans in what would become Indiana were the French inhabitants of Vincennes, and they were ruled by a governor, Arthur St. Clair; a secretary; and three judges, all appointed by the president with the consent of the Senate. The governor and judges had the power to pass all necessary laws by adopting laws from the already established states; the governor also had the power to appoint all civil officers at the county level. In 1798 the Northwest Territory entered into its second stage, permitting the establishment of a bicameral General Assembly, which, meeting in joint session, would select a nonvoting delegate to the U.S. Congress. One half of the General Assembly was a House of Representatives, made up of men who were elected for two-year terms by all free men over twenty-one holding fifty or more acres of land. The second half was a Legislative Council, whose membership was selected as follows: The House would draw up a list of ten candidates, from whom the resident would select five. In this second stage, the governor retained the right to select county officials, but the General Assembly defined the powers of these offices. For most of modern Indiana, this second stage of self-government was short-lived; in 1800, the Indiana Territory, which included present-day Indiana, Wisconsin, Illinois, and the western half of Michigan, most of the state was split from the Northwest Territory. Because few European Americans lived in this new territory, it was organized once again without representative government, with William Henry Harrison appointed governor (1800–1813) and governing much as the Northwest Territory had been governed in its first stage. In 1803 the state of Ohio was formed from the Northwest Territory, and a small "gore" east of the Greenville Treaty line was added to Indiana Territory, together with the eastern half of present-day Michigan.</p>
            <p>The 1800 act establishing Indiana Territory provided for the residents of Indiana to move to the second stage of territorial government without regard to population, if the move was the will of the people. In 1804, in an election in which only 400 hundred votes were cast, Indiana residents signaled their desire to move into the second stage, and in 1805, Governor Harrison set into motion the creation of a General Assembly with seven members in the House of Representatives. In the midst of moving to the second stage, Michigan was established as a separate territory by Congress in 1805. In accommodating the desires of European American residents, Harrison showed greater wisdom than Arthur St. Clair, who had attempted to slow the progression of the Northwest Territory into statehood until two Federalist states could be created. Harrison, though initially appointed by Federalist Adams, won the favor of Jeffersonian Republicans and was reappointed by both Jefferson and Madison. Despite his ability to navigate national politics, Harrison was unable to avoid the distrust of his executive power that lay at the heart of the earlier conflicts with St. Clair; much of this suspicion revolved around the issue of the introduction of slavery into the territory. Even before Harrison's arrival in Indiana, some in the territory had sought to repeal the Ordinance of 1787's ban on slavery in the territory, and Harrison allied himself with the effort to repeal. Congress was deaf to these petitions, but in both the first and the second stage, Harrison and his allies passed laws that introduced African American servitude. As the territory became more settled, a regional split appeared; those living in southeastern and south central Indiana tended to oppose slavery, whereas those living in the Wabash Valley and the Illinois country tended to support slavery. Eventually, the supporters of slavery themselves were split: Illinois country supporters believed that being a separate territory, and ultimately a separate state, would best bring slavery to their communities. Thus Harrison and his Wabash Valley allies were left in a minority in Indiana Territory when Illinois Territory was created in 1809, leaving Indiana with approximately its modern boundaries, plus a segment of the Upper Peninsula of modern Michigan. The easterner-versus-westerner split in Indiana politics would remain evident for some time.</p>
            <p>Indianans repeatedly petitioned the U.S. Congress for a more democratic territorial government. In 1808 Congress extended the suffrage to those owning town lots and those in the act of purchasing public lands, but the act specifically excluded nonwhites. In 1809 Congress provided for the direct election of the Legislative Council and of the nonvoting delegate to the Congress. In 1811 Congress further extended the suffrage to all white men over twenty-one who had paid a local tax and who had resided in the territory for one year. In 1811 the territorial General Assembly changed the method of voting from viva voce to ballot. About this time, Harrison, who had been accused abusing his power over local officials, acceded to popular will and began holding extralegal elections for sheriff when vacancies occurred, appointing the winners. Harrison resigned in the midst of the War of 1812, and Madison appointed Thomas Posey governor (1813–1816); Virginian Posey reassured Indianans that he opposed slavery. The forces that had opposed slavery in Indiana Territory had already begun to drive toward statehood, coalescing behind congressional delegate (1809–1816) Jonathan Jennings. As early as 1811, Indiana petitioned to become a state, which in the minds of many residents would assure them of their full rights as citizens of a democratic republic.</p>
            <p>In 1816 Congress authorized Indiana to write a state constitution. Responding to the belief that the territorial governors exercised excessive powers, the framers of this constitution provided for a weak governor, one whose vetoes could be overridden by a simple majority in both houses of the state legislature, which was a General Assembly composed of a Senate, one-third of whose members were elected each year, and a House of Representatives, whose members were elected annually. The governor was also elected for a three-year term, and there was a separate elected office of lieutenant governor. The other executive officers (secretary of state, auditor, and treasurer and the presiding judges of the circuit courts were elected by joint ballot of both houses of the legislature. The governor did appoint, with the consent of the Senate, the three justices on the state supreme court. County officials, including the associate judges for each county, were popularly elected. The suffrage was further extended to all white men over twenty-one who had lived in the state for one year, and all voting was to take place by ballot. (The state constitution gave the 1821 legislature the one-time option of changing the voting to viva voce; that option was not exercised.)</p>
            <p>Rewarded for his shepherding in Congress of Indiana's democratic desires, Jonathan Jennings was elected the new state's first governor. By his second term, concerns about his improper exercise of executive power began to coalesce. Jennings was closely allied with the State Bank created in 1816, and concerns over its failure in the wake of the Panic of 1819 raised concerns about Jennings as well. He nevertheless was elected to the U.S. Congress in 1822, taking the place of Williams Hendricks, who had resigned the congressional seat to become governor (1822–1825). Jennings was concurrently elected to one of the three new congressional seats established after the 1820 census redistricting. This horse-trading of offices, combined with the bank’s failure and the use of patronage by both Hendricks and Jennings, stirred dissatisfaction among an unorganized cohort of Indiana voters. Such dissatisfaction began to coalesce around the presidential candidacy of Andrew Jackson, and in 1824, the voters in Indiana had their first opportunity to vote for presidential electors (the legislature had picked Indiana's Monroe electors in 1816 and 1824), and Jackson captured 47 percent of the vote. Despite supporting either Clay or Adams, men such as Jennings, Hendricks, and James Noble (U.S. Senator, 1816–1831) retained sufficient popular appeal because of their role in leading Indiana to statehood.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Barnhart, John D. and Dorothy Riker. <title>Indiana to 1816: The Colonial Period. Volume 1 of The History of Indiana.</title> Indianapolis: Indiana Historical Society, 1971.</li>
                <li>Carmony, Donald F. <title>Indiana, 1816–1850: The Pioneer Era. Volume 2 of The History of Indiana.</title> Indianapolis: Indiana Historical Bureau and Indiana Historical Society, 1998.</li>
                <li>Mills, Randy Keith. <title>Jonathan Jennings: Indiana's First Governor.</title> Indianapolis: Indiana Historical Society, 2005.</li>
                <li>"Indiana Documents Leading to Statehood."  <a href="http://www.statelib.lib.in.us/www/ihb/resources/document.html">Indiana Historical Bureau. </a></li>
                <li>"Road to Indiana Statehood."  <a href="http://indiamond6.ulib.iupui.edu/cdm4/browse.php?CISOROOT=%2FISC">The Digital Collections of IUPUI Library.</a></li>
                <li>Nation, Richard F. <title>At Home in the Hoosier Hills: Agriculture, Politics, and Religion in Southern Indiana, 1810–1870.</title> Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2005.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Kentucky">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Matthew Schoenbachler<br/>
                University of Northern Alabama
            </div>
            <p>Kentucky, never having been a territory, broke off from Virginia to become the nation's fifteenth state in 1792. Its first constitution, drafted that year, was soon found unsatisfactory, and a second constitution was framed in 1799. Despite the presence of a few prominent Federalists, Kentucky was a virtual one-party state, with the Jeffersonian Republicans dominating throughout the era of the First Party System. This ostensible political unanimity, however, masked substantial political conflict throughout the state's early history, antagonisms that exploded in the wake of the Panic of 1819.</p>
            <p>The first white settlers moved into Kentucky on the eve of the Revolutionary War, and the region remained the westernmost district of Virginia for almost twenty years. After extensive negotiations—including several enabling acts passed by the Virginian Assembly and a seemingly endless series of state conventions convened to discuss the terms of separation and the structure of the proposed state government—Kentucky finally secured its independence from Virginia in 1792.</p>
            <p>Late that spring, a state constitutional convention, dominated by the well-connected and aristocratic George Nicholas, convened at Danville and finished its work in less than three weeks. Kentucky's first constitution has often been characterized as a forward-looking product of the democratic frontier, and many of its features do support this view: The document abolished all religious qualifications, incorporated a comprehensive Bill of Rights, prohibited viva voce voting, provided for the annual election of state representatives, and, most notably, granted universal white adult male suffrage. Yet the decision to lift property requirements for voting had as much to do with extraordinary high rates of landlessness and rampant confusion over land titles as it did with democratic enthusiasm; the delegates did not dare disfranchise well over half of the state's population. In fact, a majority of the convention was determined to contain the swiftly moving democratic currents of the early republic, and they leaned heavily on Pennsylvania's 1790 constitution—itself a conservative revision of the state's far more radical 1776 constitution. The document, therefore, created a powerful executive, one chosen by electors every four years and possessed of substantial powers of appointment; a bicameral General Assembly in which the upper house would also be decided by an electoral college; and a nonelective judiciary. Significantly, the constitution gave original and final jurisdiction over land cases to the state supreme court, a provision that the great landowners of Kentucky had advocated for years because it precluded any chance for appeal. Furthermore, conservative elements at the convention turned back an attempt to end slavery in the state and, in fact, secured a positive and explicit protection for slavery, the first such constitutional provision in the nation.</p>
            <p>The delegates, apparently not overly confident in their handiwork, included an unusual provision for another constitutional convention seven years hence if "it shall seem expedient." Sure enough, many Kentuckians soon became convinced that fundamental changes to the state's supreme law were not only expedient but necessary. Proposed reforms ranged from the relatively mild suggestion that members of the county courts be prohibited from serving in the legislature to more radical demands for the emancipation of slaves, the abolition of the governorship and the Senate, a complete overhaul of the state's court system, and a renunciation of the separation agreement with Virginia that protected the property rights of nonresident landholders.</p>
            <p>And so, in 1799, the state's voters authorized a second state constitutional convention. This time, John Breckinridge, a Virginia-born lawyer soon to be Thomas Jefferson's attorney general, dominated the proceedings in much the same way that Nicholas commanded the first convention. Under Breckinridge's guidance, the conservatives succeeded in curbing the most radical demands for reform: The legislature remained bicameral, the separation agreement with Virginia was upheld, the attempt to reform the judiciary and its control of land titles was turned back, and slavery was once again protected and preserved. Although delegates made some concessions to popular sovereignty (including the direct election of the governor and state senators), they reinstated viva voce voting, preserved the appointment of judges, and made other minor offices, previously elective, appointive. To cap things off, the conservatives included a clause that made further revision of the constitution extremely difficult.</p>
            <p>Throughout its first thirty years, Kentucky overwhelmingly supported the Republican Party. In 1798, when Vice President Thomas Jefferson needed a friendly venue to channel anonymously his resolutions condemning the Alien and Sedition Acts, he naturally turned to the legislature of Kentucky. Although a nominal Federalist Party did exist in the state, and a few of its adherents managed to secure election, the Republican Party's dominance was virtually unchallenged.</p>
            <p>But however monolithic Kentucky's political structure may have been, by no means did this translate into political consensus. Several issues proved to be immensely contentious in the state's early years: the establishment of a state circuit court system in 1803, the creation and spread of a banking system in the first two decades of the nineteenth century, and the controversy in 1817 over whether the death of a sitting governor necessitated a new election. One traveler in 1807 amused himself in a Lexington coffee house by perusing "the wonderful mass of political contradiction to be found in forty different newspapers, where scarcely any two editors coincided in opinion."</p>
            <p>But it was the financial ruin that descended upon the country in 1819 that triggered early Kentucky's most divisive and vehement political conflict. In the wake of bank failures, sheriff's sales, and ruinous deflation, the state's citizens demanded that the state government alleviate their suffering. By 1821 the General Assembly had constructed a relief system that allowed debtors to postpone repayment of debt, created a Commonwealth's Bank that generously lent paper money, and mandated that any property sold under execution must bring three-quarters of its pre-depression value. An Anti-Relief faction appeared almost immediately, vehemently insisting that the state and federal constitutions prohibited such legislation. After the state courts struck down major portions of the relief system in 1823 and 1824, the General Assembly responded by actually attempting to abolish the state high court (the Court of Appeals) and establish a new court more to their liking. It was, as it turned out, a bridge too far, for in the next year's elections, the "Old Court" Anti-Relief candidates decisively defeated the "New Court" pro-relief slate. In early 1827, the new legislature restored the original court, thus bringing to an end the state's notorious Relief War. In the 1830s, Kentucky reverted to its traditional one-party status, as the Whig Party came to dominate the state's politics for another generation.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Aron, Steven. <title>How the West Was Lost: The Transformation of Kentucky from Daniel Boone to Henry Clay.</title> Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996.</li>
                <li>Coward, Joan Wells. <title>Kentucky in the New Republic: The Process of Constitution Making.</title> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1979.</li>
                <li>Ellis, Richard. <title>The Jeffersonian Crisis: Courts and Politics in the Young Republic.</title> New York: Norton, 1971.</li>
                <li>Friend, Craig Thompson. <title>Along the Maysville Road: The Early American Republic in the Trans-Appalachian West.</title> Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 2005.</li>
                <li>Harrison, Lowell H. <title>Kentucky's Road to Statehood.</title> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1992.</li>  
                <li>Tachau, Mary K. Bonsteel. <title>Federal Courts in the Early Republic: Kentucky 1789-1816.</title> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1978.</li>
                <li>Teute, Fredrika Johanna. <title>Land, Liberty, and Labor in the Post-Revolutionary Era: Kentucky as the Promised Land.</title> Ph.D. dissertation, Johns Hopkins University, 1988.</li>
                <li>Watlington, Patricia. <title>The Partisan Spirit: Kentucky Politics, 1779–1792.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1972.</li> 
                <li>Young, Bennett H. <title>History and Texts of the Three Constitutions of Kentucky.</title> Louisville, KY: Courier Journal Job Printing Co., 1890.</li>    
                <li><a href="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/award99/icuhtml/fawhome.html">First American West</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://history.ky.gov/">Kentucky Historical Society</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://www.filsonhistorical.org/">Filson Club Historical Society</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://www.kyvl.org/">Kentucky Virtual Library</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://kdl.kyvl.org/">Kentuckiana Digital Library </a></li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/11_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   The Old Court / New Court Struggle</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/08_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   The Boundary</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/07_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   The Dueling Oath</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/06_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   Housekeeping</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/05_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   Henry Clay and Homespun cloth</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/04_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   Kentucky Resolutions</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.lrc.state.ky.us/record/Moments04RS/01_web_leg_history.html">Moments in Kentucky Legislative History</a>   First Session</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Louisiana">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Excerpt from the New Advent Catholic Encyclopedia “Louisiana” 
            </div>
            <p>The State of Louisiana, lying at the mouth of the Mississippi, was so named in honour of Louis XIV in 1682. Louisiana of the seventeenth century extended from the Mississippi River to the Rocky Mountains, and from the Rio Grande and Gulf of Mexico to BritishAmerica. The cession of Louisiana by France to the United States took place on 20 December, 1803, and in 1804, Congress organized the territory of Orléans, which comprised a portion of the great district of Louisiana. In 1806 there were but 350 English-speaking white men in New Orleans. Between 1806 and 1809, 3100 Americans arrived. In 1809-10 came the immigration from the West Indies, due to the Santo Domingo and Haitian negro uprisings. In 1810 the Irish began to come, and they kept coming steadily for over forty years. </p>   
            <p>In 1811 Congress authorized the inhabitants of the territory to draw up a constitution, with a view to establish a state government. The constitution was adopted in 1812, and immediately thereafter, on 30 April 1812, Congress admitted Louisiana to the Union. Almost simultaneously with her admission, the war with England broke out, and on 8 January 1815, the famous battle of New Orleans, between 12,000 English soldiers under Pakenham and 5000 American recruits under Andrew Jackson, was fought within a few miles of the city of New Orleans, resulting in the overwhelming defeat of the British.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09378a.htm">“Louisiana” New Advent Catholic Encyclopedia, 2007</a></li>
                
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Maine">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Joshua M. Smith<br/>
                U.S. Merchant Marine Academy
            </div>       
            <p>The pursuit of statehood dominated Maine politics between 1787 and 1820, when it finally achieved statehood separate from Massachusetts. Until 1820, the District of Maine simply comprised the eastern counties of the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and thus shared all its political characteristics (see Massachusetts entry). There were significant efforts at statehood in 1788–1789, 1792, 1803, 1816, but the district's populous coastal communities proved unwilling to sever their connections with the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>After 1803 the statehood issue increasingly became identified with Jeffersonianism. Backcountry residents became increasingly restive, in no small part because of antipathy to absentee proprietors who owned vast swathes of Maine's undeveloped hinterland. The situation remained volatile until the issue became politicized by Jeffersonian leaders who saw a chance to land a major blow against the Boston-based Federalist elite. The dominant figure in the struggle for statehood was William King, a wealthy merchant who based his political career on the grievances of squatters and religious dissenters such as himself. In a timely defection, in 1803 he became a Republican, portending the district's conversion; in 1805 the District of Maine voted for a Jeffersonian gubernatorial candidate, and a majority of its voters never supported Federalism thereafter.</p>
            <p>The War of 1812 proved a catalyst for statehood. Militarily abandoned by Massachusetts, Mainers increasingly realized that only statehood would endow them with a political voice. Yet an 1816 statehood effort failed. Stung by the defeat, King realized that Maine's coastal communities would not break with old Massachusetts as a consequence of a peculiarity in federal navigation laws. Utilizing his political connections in Washington, King helped refashion national maritime policies in such a way that separation did not threaten the shipping trades so essential to Maine's coastal communities. With this obstacle removed, in July 1819 an election based on separation passed in all nine Maine counties; by October, representatives held a constitutional convention.</p>
            <p>Maine's constitution departed significantly from that of Massachusetts and can be seen as a triumph of Jeffersonian principles. It guaranteed freedom of both speech and press; absolute freedom of religion; and universal male suffrage for those over twenty-one, with no property qualifications whatever and no racial restrictions. Maine's legislature was bicameral, featuring a House of Representatives and a Senate, with November elections every two years for both houses. Unlike Massachusetts, which, to ensure the dominance of Suffolk County, based the number of senators on each county’s wealth, Maine apportioned senators on the basis of population.</p>
            <p>The new state's executive powers were somewhat altered from those of old Massachusetts, which arguably had the strongest governorship in the nation, but they nonetheless remained strong. Governors were not required to be Christians, and they served a four-year term. There was no lieutenant governor; the president of the Senate was designated the successor to any governor incapacitated. The combined Senate and House elected a seven-member council to assist the governor.</p>
            <p>Congress approved Maine's statehood in 1820 as part of the "Missouri Compromise." Given his prominence in the statehood movement, it is appropriate that King became Maine's first governor.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Banks, Ronald F. <title>Maine Becomes a State: The Movement to Separate Maine from Massachusetts, 1785–1820.</title> Middletown, CT: Published for the Maine Historical Society by Wesleyan University Press, 1970.</li>
                <li>Formisano, Ronald P. <title>The Transformation of Political Culture: Massachusetts Parties, 1790s–1840s.</title> New York: Oxford University Press, 1983.</li>
                <li>Goodman, Paul. <title>The Democratic-Republicans of Massachusetts; Politics in a Young Republic.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1964.</li>
                <li>Leamon, James S. <title>Revolution Downeast: The War for American Independence in Maine.</title> Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 1993.</li>
                <li>Marini, Stephen A. <title>Radical Sects of Revolutionary New England.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1982.</li>
                <li>Taylor, Alan. <title>Liberty Men and Great Proprietors: The Revolutionary Settlement on the Maine Frontier, 1760–1820.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1990. Published for the Institute of Early American History and Culture, Williamsburg, Virginia.</li>
                <li>Williamson, William D. <title>The History of the State of Maine: From Its First Discovery, A.D. 1602, to the Separation, A.D. 1820, Inclusive.</title> Hallowell, ME: Glazier, Masters and Co., 1832.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Maryland">
        <div class="byline">
            Written by Philip Lampi
        </div>
        <history>
            <p>On April 28, 1788, the Maryland Legislature, by a vote of 63 to 11, became the seventh state to ratify the new proposed national Constitution.</p>
            <p>With the creation of Allegany on December 25, 1789, the number of counties in Maryland increased to nineteen, a number that stayed constant until 1837. In addition, Baltimore and Annapolis were classified as cities.</p>
            <p>Maryland had three Legislative bodies. The House of Delegates, which was elected annually in October, had eighty members; four were chosen at large from each county and two from both Baltimore City and Annapolis.</p>
            <p>A State Senate of fifteen members was chosen every five years in early September and by an unusual method. An Electoral College of forty members was chosen, consisting of two members from the counties and one each from Baltimore City and Annapolis. The Electoral College then voted to elect nine Senators to represent the Western Counties and six for what was termed the Eastern Shore. There was not much interest in these elections until 1801, when for the first time; they became a political contest between the Federalist and Republican parties.</p>
            <p>In addition to the above, a Governor’s Council of five members was elected annually by a joint session of the House of Delegates and State Senate. They assisted the Governor who was also chosen yearly by the Legislature.</p>
            <p>Since the House of Delegates and State Senate voted together in electing the Governor, United States Senators and Governor’s Council, a potentially difficult situation could arise, if control of these two bodies was split between both parties. This played out in the election of 1800, when for the first time, Republicans won control of the House of Delegates, but Federalists still controlled the State Senate. As a result, the Federalists were able to elect their Governor, United States Senator and the entire Governor’s Council, even though Republicans had clearly won the state election.</p>
            <p>Popular elections were held in Maryland for Congress, Presidential Electors, House of Delegates, State Senator Electors and County Sheriff. After the elections of 1788 and 1792, all Congressmen and Presidential Electors were chosen by districts. In addition, popular elections for city officers were held in Baltimore and Annapolis.</p>
            <p>Except for the overwhelming Republican vote from Baltimore City, the parties were over all fairly evenly matched. After losing control of the state in 1801, the Federalists stayed relatively competitive and were able to rebound and capture the House of Delegates in 1808, and again from 1812–1817. Their greatest victory came in 1816 when they elected five out of nine congressmen, all fifteen State Senators, and had a 56 to 24 edge in the House of Delegates.</p>
            <p>With their large majorities in the House of Delegates after 1812 and then by winning the State Senate in 1816, the Federalists were able to elect their Governors and Council members from 1812–1818 along with two United States Senators, one in 1813 and another in 1816. For several years they were in complete control of the Maryland Government.</p>
            <p>By 1819 the Federalists lost their majority in the House of Delegates and two years later the entire State Senate.  Only fourteen Federalists were elected to the House of Delegates in 1823. However, the following year in an unexpected turn of events, Federalists ran candidates in seven of the eight congressional contests, electing three members and losing another by running two candidates, splitting their votes, thus allowing a Republican to win.  Voter turnout for this election was the highest ever cast in Maryland. It was perhaps a precursor to the changing political scene that was about to engulf the nation.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.thingstodo.com/states/MD/history.htm">"State History", Maryland, Things to do.com, (2006)Software Solutions </a></li>
                <li>Archives of Maryland<a href="http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/speccol/sc2600/sc2685/html/histlist2.html"> Historical List Maryland Government</a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Massachusetts">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Matthew H. Crocker<br/>
                Keene State College
            </div>       
            <p>With independence from Great Britain in 1776, the Commonwealth of Massachusetts was governed by the same bicameral legislature that existed during the colonial period. It was not until 1780 that John Adams, armed with a statewide mandate for a constitutional convention, set about drafting a formal state constitution. What Adams forged proved so successful that it later became a template for the Constitution of United States. What made the 1780 Massachusetts constitution so influential was how it seemingly balanced the populist ideals promised to the citizenry by the Revolution with the fundamentally conservative expectations of the existing Massachusetts elite. In terms of structure, it established an elective chief magistrate (the governor), a bicameral legislature (the General Court made up of a House and a Senate), and an independent judiciary (an appointed state court system). Also, Adams included a declaration of rights to ensure civil liberties (as well as his brainchild's ratification). Although ratified by town meetings throughout the commonwealth, the document was fundamentally conservative in that it secured the ruling elite's control over the state by giving disproportionate power to the wealthy coastal counties of Suffolk and Essex. Not surprisingly, the 1780 constitution became the darling of the Federalist Party establishment that fought to resist constitutional reform. In opposition, the Democratic-Republicans chafed at the propertied basis for representation in the Senate, which gave an eastern county like Suffolk six senators to Berkshire's two, despite the fact that Berkshire had a larger population. Also, the Democratic-Republicans, whose popular base was in the western part of the state and tended to be of modest means, despised the pecuniary qualifications for the franchise, as well as the nonelected judiciary, claiming both were profoundly undemocratic. </p>
            <p>In 1820 the opponents to the 1780 constitution had their chance when the Maine district of Massachusetts was broken off and given statehood. As a result of such radical change, the General Court called for a constitutional convention to revisit the constitution of 1780. Despite optimistic expectations for major constitutional reform, an assortment of conservatives, led by a highly sophisticated Federalist Party machine, outwitted the forces of reform at the convention, and little significant change was effected. Power remained centralized in the east, with Boston serving as its epicenter. Although the state constitutional convention proved a great victory for the Federalist establishment, in the early 1820s the party faced an angry populist insurgency fed up with the dictatorial leadership style of the Federalists. In Boston a third party, the Middling Interest, emerged that rejected the deferential nature of past politics and took up an activist stand for reform. In the mayoral election of 1822, the insurgency forced Federalist Party boss Harrison Gray Otis to bow out of the race and elected a Middling Interest candidate, thus marking the demise of the Federalist Party in Massachusetts. Although it still existed in name for a few more years, the party never regained its once dominant position in Massachusetts political life, thus signaling the advent of the Jacksonian Age and the Second Party System.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <title></title>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Banner, James M., Jr. <title>To the Hartford Convention: The Federalist and the Origins of Politics in Massachusetts. </title>New York: Knopf, 1970.</li>
                <li>Brooke, John L. <title>The Heart of the Commonwealth: Society and Political Culture in Worchester County, Massachusetts, 1713–1861</title> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989.</li>
                <li>Brown, Richard D. and Jack Tager. <title>Massachusetts: A Concise History.</title> Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 2000.</li>
                <li>Cayton, Andrew R. L. <title>"The Fragmentation of 'A Great Family': The Panic of 1819 and the Rise of the Middling Interest in Boston, 1818–1822,"</title> Journal of the Early Republic, 2 (Summer 1982), 143–167.</li>
                <li>Clark, Christopher. <title>The Roots of Rural Capitalism: Western Massachusetts, 1780–1860</title> Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1990.</li>  
                <li>Crocker, Matthew H. <title>The Magic of the Many: Josiah Quincy and the Rise of Mass Politics in Boston, 1800–1830.</title> Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 2000.</li>
                <li>Crocker, Matthew H. <title>"'The Siege of Boston is once more raised'": Municipal Politics and the Collapse of Federalism, 1821–1823,"</title> in <title>Massachusetts Politics: Selected Essays, ed.</title> Jack Tager, Martin Kaufman, and Michael F. Konig. Westfield, MA: Institute for Massachusetts Studies Press, 1998, pp. 52–71.</li>
                <li>Dalzell, Robert F., Jr. <title>Enterprising Elite, The Boston Associates and the World They Made.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1987.</li> 
                <li>Fisher, David Hackett. <title>The Revolution of American Conservatism: The Federalist Party in the Era of Jeffersonian Democracy.</title> New York: Harper Torchbooks, 1965.</li>
                <li>Formisano, Ronald P. <title>The Transformation of Political Culture: Massachusetts Parties, 1790s–1840s</title> New York: Oxford University Press, 1983.</li>
                <li>Handlin, Oscar and Mary Flug Handlin. <title>Commonwealth: Study of the Role of Government in the American Economy, 1774–1861, rev. ed.</title> Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1969.</li>
                <li>Hartford, William F. <title>Money, Morals, and Politics: Massachusetts in the Age of the Boston Associates.</title> Boston: Northeastern University Press, 2001.</li>
                <li>McCaughey, Robert A. <title>Josiah Quincy, 1772–1864: The Last Federalist.</title> Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1974.</li>
                <li>Morison, Samuel Eliot. <title>Harrison Gray Otis, 1765–1848: The Urbane Federalist.</title> Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1969.</li>
                <li>Morison, Samuel Eliot. <title>The Maritime History of Massachusetts, 1783–1860.</title> Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1961.</li>
                <li>Peterson, Merrill D., ed. <title>Democracy, Liberty, and Property: The State Constitutional Conventions of the 1820's.</title> New York: Bobbs-Merrill, 1966.</li>
                <li>Sheidley, Harlow W. <title>Sectional Nationalism: Massachusetts Conservative Leaders and the Transformation of America, 1815–1836.</title> Boston: Northeastern University Press, 1998.</li>
                <li>Smith, Page. <title>John Adams: 1784–1826, Vol. II.</title> Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1962.</li>
                <li>Story, Ronald. <title>Harvard and the Boston Upper Class: The Forging of an Aristocracy, 1800–1870</title> Middletown, CN: Wesleyan University Press, 1980.</li>
                <li>Wilkie, Richard W. and Jack Tager, eds. <title>Historical Atlas of Massachusetts.</title> Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 1991.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Michigan">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by William S. Belko<br/>
                University of West Florida
            </div>      
            <p>The most distinctive facet of Michigan territorial politics from 1787 to 1825 was the pursuit of representative government, specifically the adoption of a popularly elected legislature—a feature essentially denied the citizens of Michigan Territory until statehood in January of 1837. Michigan politics originated with the Northwest Ordinance of 1787, when the area that would become the state of Michigan entered the first stage of territorial government as stipulated in that seminal document. In 1798 the Northwest Territory reached the second stage of territorial government, allowing minimal representative government in the form of a popularly elected territorial legislature and a somewhat elective territorial council. Detroit, essentially the sole population center in Michigan, held its first American election that year, electing Solomon Sibley as a delegate to the territorial legislature located in Cincinnati; voters sent two more representatives in early 1799. In 1800 Congress divided the future Michigan Territory in half, the eastern region remaining part of the Northwest Territory and the western region entering Indiana Territory. When Congress granted Ohio statehood in 1803, however, it excluded all of present-day Michigan, adding it instead to Indiana Territory. The reason given for such an unwarranted move was that Detroit was heavily Federalist, yet Ohio was solidly Jeffersonian Republican, thus guaranteeing the Republican Party another set of electoral votes and congressional representation. The change greatly angered Michiganders, because Indiana Territory was still in the first stage of government and thus without a representative body. Michiganders petitioned Congress for the creation of a new territory, and Congress complied. Michigan officially became a territory effective June 30, 1805.</p>
            <p>While the region was still in the first stage of government, Jefferson appointed and Congress confirmed the new territorial leaders: four individuals who had full powers of lawmaking and administration, subject only to congressional approval. Even though President Jefferson appointed all of them, antipathy quickly developed among the territorial officials. Governor William Hull from Massachusetts, who actually had Federalist leanings, warred from the start with one of the three territorial judges, Augustus Woodward from Virginia. Animosity escalated when, in 1808, Judge James Witherell from Vermont joined Hull, and Judge John Griffin from Virginia sided with Woodward. With the New Englanders united against the Virginians–all Republicans in the Federalist stronghold of Detroit–the open and constant feuding resulted in outright governmental deadlock. Infuriated with both factions, Michigan citizens campaigned for an elected legislature, beginning in 1809 when a Detroit grand jury petitioned Congress for a change in territorial status. Congress's preoccupation with impending war with England, however, doomed any alterations. British occupation during the War of 1812 only worsened the political scene in Michigan, and with American reoccupation in 1814, Michiganders immediately renewed their pursuit of representative government.</p>
            <p>In 1818 the new territorial governor, Lewis Cass, organized an election in which voters, as a consequence of the heavy French turnout, rejected the move for a popularly elected legislature. New England settlers demanded more representative government, but the old French and British elements in Detroit had no inclination for self-government. Congress did authorize, in 1819, the direct election of a nonvoting delegate to Congress. Voters included all adult white males who were taxpayers and had met the one-year residency requirement. In 1823 Congress again acceded to Michigan's demand for more representative government by allowing the election of a Legislative Council, a feature inherent in the second stage of territorial government. Michigan voters nominated eighteen individuals for the territorial council, and the president, with the advice and consent of the Senate, chose nine. The Legislative Council held all lawmaking powers, subject only to the governor's veto and congressional sanction. Congress made several other moves to meet Michigan's demands. In 1825, it authorized qualified voters in each county to choose all county officials except judges, and it allowed town meetings to become the governing bodies in the townships. In 1827 Congress expanded the Legislative Council to thirteen members and made them all directly elected by Michigan citizens. Still, Michiganders had been denied an elected House of Representatives during its territorial period, gaining only nominal self-government under the unicameral Legislative Council.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Bald, F. Clever. <title>Detroit's First American Decade, 1796 to 1805.</title> Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1948.</li>
                <li>Dunbar, Willis F. and George S. May. <title>Michigan: A History of the Wolverine State, 3rd rev. ed.</title> Grand Rapids: William B. Eerdmans, 1995.</li>
                <li>Gilpin, Alec R. <title>The Territory of Michigan [1805–1837].</title> East Lansing: Michigan State University Press, 1970.</li>
                <li>Sherer, Timothy. <title>"The Resistance to Representative Government in Early Michigan Territory."</title> The Old Northwest, 5(2)(1979): 167–179.</li>
                <li>Woodford, Frank B. <title>Mr. Jefferson's Disciple: A Life of Justice Woodward.</title> East Lansing: Michigan State College Press, 1953.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Mississippi">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Philip Lampi<br/>
            </div>    
            <p>The Mississippi Territory was established on April 7, 1798 from land ceded by Spain to the United States in 1795. The original area comprised about half the present states of Alabama and Mississippi. The size of this Territory grew substantially in 1804 with the cession of land from Georgia, and again in 1812 with annexation of the Mobile District from Spanish West Florida.  With this final land acquisition the territory would encompass the entire present day states of Alabama and Mississippi.</p>
            <p>Members of the Territorial Legislature were elected by popular vote, but other State and Federal officials were appointed either by the President, Congress or the Territorial Legislature. The first popular election for a Territory Delegate to Congress took place in October 1808.</p>
            <p>The first Territorial Governor, appointed by President Adams was Winthrop Sargent, a Federalist from Massachusetts.  With the election in 1801 of Thomas Jefferson as President, Winthrop Sargent was replaced by William C. Claiborne, a Republican from Tennessee.</p>
            <p>During the term of Winthrop Sargent, Natchez was the Territorial capitol. It was moved to nearby Washington shortly after the appointment of William C. Claiborne, and in 1822 to accommodate the rapidly expanding population; the capitol was permanently moved at Jackson.</p>
            <p>By Federal statues of March 1, and 3, 1817, a plan to divide the Mississippi Territory into two separate entities was set in motion. After setting boundaries, the western area began the process of organizing for statehood.</p>
            <p>On July 7, 1817 a Convention of 48 delegates convened at Washington, Mississippi to write a State Constitution, which was adopted on August 15, 1817. The first state elections were held on September 1 and 2, 1817. Mississippi was admitted to the Union on December 10, 1817.</p>
            <p>Under the State Constitution, future state elections would take place in early August. The Governor and Lieutenant Governor were chosen by popular vote, serving for two years. Members to the House of Representatives were elected annually and State Senators for three years. Local officials like Sheriff and Coroners were also chosen at this time. Various other state officials were chosen by the Legislature. On the federal level, Mississippi’s one Congressman was also elected in August and their Presidential Electors were to be chosen at large by popular vote.</p>
            <p>For the first decade of statehood, much of Mississippi was still Indian land, and with the exception of northern Monroe County, which had been cut off from Madison County, now in Alabama, all the organized counties were in the southern part of the state or along the lower Mississippi River.</p>
            <p>Although the state was politically Republican, there still may have been some lingering Federalist influence around the Natchez area from the days of Winthrop Sargent. It is interesting to note that in the 1824 election for President, two thirds of the vote for John Adams, came from the five oldest counties in the state, being Adams, Claiborne, Jefferson, Warren and Wilkinson, all of which were along the Mississippi River.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Bettersworth, John K. <title>Mississippi: A History.</title> Austin: The Steck Company, 1959.</li>
                <li>Bettersworth, John K. and James W. Silver, eds. <title>Mississippi in the Confederacy.</title> Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1961.</li>
                <li>Bunn, Mike and Clay Williams, "Capitals and Capitols:The Places and Spaces of Mississippi’s Seat of Government"<a href="http://mshistory.k12.ms.us/features/feature44/capitals_capitols.html">Mississippi History Now </a></li>
                <li>Clark, Thomas D. and John D.W. Guice. <title>The Old Southwest, 1795–1830.</title> Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1996.</li>
                <li>Cox, James L. <title>The Mississippi Almanac.</title> Yazoo City: Computer Search and Research, 2001.</li>
                <li>Cross, Ralph D., Robert W. Wales, and Charles T. Traylor. <title>Atlas of Mississippi.</title> Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, 1974.</li>
                <li>Gleason, David K., Mary Warren Miller, and Ronald W. Miller. <title>The Great Houses of Natchez.</title> Jackson: University of Mississippi Press, 1986.</li>
                <li>James, D. Clayton. <title>Antebellum Natchez.</title> Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1968.</li>
                
                <li>Lowry, Robert and William H. McCardle. <title>A History of Mississippi</title>. Spartanburg, SC: The Reprint Company, 1978.</li>
                <li>McCain, William D. <title>The Story of Jackson.</title> Jackson: J.F. Hyer, 1953.</li>
                <li>McLemore, Richard A., ed. <title>A History of Mississippi, Vol. 1.</title> Jackson: University &amp; College Press of Mississippi, 1973.</li>
                <li>Rowland, Dunbar. <title>History of Mississippi.</title> Spartanburg, SC: The Reprint Company, 1978.</li>
                <li>________. <title>Mississippi Territorial Archives, Vol. 1.</title> Nashville, TN: Press of Brandon Printing Company, 1905.</li>
                <li>Sansing, David G., Sim C. Callon, and Carolyn V. Smith. <title></title>Natchez: An Illustrated History. Natchez, MS: Plantation Publishing Company, 1995.</li>
                <li>Skates, John Ray. <title>Mississippi’s Old Capitol: Biography of a Building.</title> Jackson: Mississippi Department of Archives and History, 1990.</li>
                <li>Sydnor, Charles S. <title>A Gentleman of the Old Natchez Region: Benjamin L. C. Wailes.</title> Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1938.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Missouri">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by William E. Foley<br/>
                University of Central Missouri
            </div>       
            <p>Missouri's political history unfolded in a world of colliding cultures and conflicting political traditions. During its early days as a borderland colony governed by imperial France and Spain, its political culture rested on a hierarchy of patrons and clients who often mixed public and private interests. After the Louisiana Purchase placed the frontier province under the authority of the United States, American officials pondered how best to maintain order and introduce a political system grounded on republican principles. To ensure an orderly process, President Thomas Jefferson briefly contemplated closing portions of Upper Louisiana to settlement and making those lands a refuge for relocated eastern Indians. That scheme went nowhere, and in 1804 Congress divided the territory into two administrative units: the District of Louisiana (Upper Louisiana) and the Territory of Orleans. As a cost-saving measure, it placed the less populous northern district that now encompasses Missouri under the jurisdiction of officials in Indiana Territory. That arrangement drew protests from local residents who objected to being subject to the dictates of absentee officials. Congress relented in 1805 and agreed to create a new Territory of Louisiana with a government of its own administered by a governor, secretary, and three superior court judges all appointed by the president.</p>
            <p>Although this somewhat authoritarian system, initially prescribed for first-stage territories in the Northwest Ordinance of 1787, found favor with old-line French Creoles and their allies, many republican-minded American newcomers pressed for the territory's prompt advancement to second-stage status. The higher classification allowed tax-paying adult white males to elect members of a territorial assembly for two-year terms and empowered them to send a nonvoting delegate to Congress for a similar period. It also created an upper chamber or legislative council consisting of nine members appointed by the president for five-year terms from a list of nominees proposed by the lower house. Before any legislation could take effect, it had to be approved by both houses and signed by the governor, who remained a presidential appointee. The 1812 statute that elevated Louisiana to a second-stage territory also changed its name to the Territory of Missouri to avoid confusion with the nation's newest state, Louisiana, which had previously been known as the Territory of Orleans.</p>
            <p>Between 1804 and 1820, bitter disagreements over Spanish land titles and mining concessions divided the territory into warring political camps competing to influence public policy on these and related matters. The contest pitted a coterie of French Creole fur traders and merchants with numerous unconfirmed Spanish land concessions and the influential American attorneys and government officials they had enlisted to their cause against a rival group of American land speculators determined to challenge the old order and its pursuit of confirmation for those contested land titles.    </p>
            <p>In Missouri's highly charged and intensely personal political culture, name calling, threats of bodily harm, and accusations of official misconduct were commonplace. Allegations of voting irregularities in the 1816 contest for territorial delegates caused the U.S. House of Representatives to vacate the results and order a new election. In the rematch that followed, an attempt to challenge political newcomer Thomas Hart Benton's eligibility to vote culminated in a duel that tragically left Charles Lucas, the promising young attorney who had raised the objection, dead by Benton's hand. Election-day antics seldom degenerated into mortal combat, but combative politics had become the order of the day. It mattered little that partisans on both sides of the territorial divide styled themselves Republicans.</p>
            <p>A rapid increase in the territorial population following the War of 1812 gave rise to growing demands for statehood. The territorial assembly's 1818 petition calling for Missouri to be admitted as a slave state triggered a contentious national debate over the extension of slavery. The Missouri Compromise of 1820 temporarily resolved the matter and paved the way for Missouri's formal admission to the Union on August 10, 1821. The new state's first constitution provided for a popularly elected governor and lieutenant governor who served four-year terms, but it barred the governor from succeeding himself. The document created a bicameral General Assembly consisting of a House of Representatives and a Senate whose members served two-year and four-year terms, respectively, and gave them the authority to override a governor's veto with an absolute majority of both houses. The framers of the 1820 Constitution ensured an independent judiciary by allowing the governor to appoint judges for life, but they also eliminated a tax-paying requirement for voting and bestowed suffrage on all adult white males who had lived in the state for at least one year before the election.</p>
            <p>In the new state's initial elections, an electorate that included many first-time voters declined to continue most members of the well-entrenched territorial political establishment in office. William Clark, celebrated co-leader of the expedition to the Pacific and highly successful territorial governor, was among the casualties when he lost his bid to become the state's first elected governor to Alexander McNair, a relative political novice. Clark, a scion of Virginia's old republican order, fell victim to a populist political dynamic that championed the common man. That lesson was not lost on Missouri's newly elected U.S. Senator Thomas Hart Benton and his cohorts, who rushed to exploit the rising democratic tide. This new generation of Missouri politicians entered the national forum just as the second American party system was beginning to take shape. Their support for a combative brand of popular democracy and for expanded economic opportunities placed them and their state in the vanguard of the emerging Jacksonian movement that would soon take center stage in the national political arena.</p> 
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Aron, Stephen. <title>American Confluence: The Missouri Frontier from Borderland to Border State.</title> Bloomington: University of Indiana Press, 2006.</li>
                <li>Foley, William E. <title>"After the Applause: William Clark's Failed 1820 Gubernatorial Campaign.”</title> Gateway Heritage, 24 (Fall 2003–Winter 2004), 104–111.
                </li>
                <li>________. <title>"The American Territorial System: Missouri's Experience."</title> Missouri Historical Review, 65 (July 1971): 403–426.</li>
                <li>________. <title>The Genesis of Missouri: From Wilderness Outpost to Statehood.</title> Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1989.</li>
                <li>________. <title>A History of Missouri: 1673–1820.</title> Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1971.</li>
                <li>McCandless, Perry. <title>A History of Missouri, 1820–1860.</title> Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1972.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="New Hampshire">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Michael Chaney<br/>
                President and CEO <br/>
                New Hampshire Political Library
            </div>      
            <p>Attitudes toward New Hampshire's form of government were shaped by the state's relationship with England and by a series of royal governors. The debate erupted in the mid-1770s and continued during the war. The fundamental ideological disagreement focused on local control versus state authority. Moreover, the competition for power among three distinct regions of New Hampshire (the seacoast and Piscataqua Valley, Merrimack Valley, and the Connecticut River Valley) animated the public debate further.</p>
            <p>Before passage of the Declaration of Independence in 1776, New Hampshire was the only province in New England without a formal charter of incorporation. New Hampshire was without legal government when the last royal governor, John Wentworth, fled in the summer of 1775 and the personal safety and future of Loyalists was in question. New Hampshire declared its independence six months before the signing of the Declaration of Independence on July 4.</p>
            <p>The Federalists, an elite party concerned about commercial interests and monetary policy for the new nation, regained power in New Hampshire in 1813 under John Taylor Gilman, who did not cooperate with President Madison's administration and did not support the war. Power for the Federalists was short-lived, as a declining economy lead to the resurgence of the Republican Party after the war.</p>
            <p>The nature of state government that evolved in New Hampshire during the nationalization of America had its roots in the desire to impose checks on state control, creating a political structure that was and continues to be decentralized. The governor heads a weak executive branch held in check to this day by a five-member Executive Council elected from five regions of the state. Moreover, the large House of Representatives, known as the General Court (400 members), ensures strong local representation and is the third largest legislative body in the world after Parliament and the United States Congress. A 24-member state Senate rounds out a bicameral legislative body.</p>
            <p>New Hampshire remains one of two states with two-year terms for governor, for members of the Executive Council, and for legislative office. The struggle in the early national period focused on local control, on limiting state and federal power, and on the proper distribution of authority. Although New Hampshire became the keystone of the federal government by voting as the ninth and ratifying state to adopt the United States Constitution in 1789, it has always cast a wary eye on federal power over states and on state power over local government.</p>
            <p>Local elections of delegates and representatives to constitutional conventions included the tactic of "binding instructions" to ensure that local representation would not be sacrificed to the state or federal government. This proved unpopular because a constitutional convention requires public discussion and reasoned decisions based on varying points of view raised at the convention. Hence the delegates need flexibility, not binding instructions. However, New Hampshire's political culture continues to be steeped in the desire to preserve local, community interests. The method of voting began with voice votes at town meetings, but by 1804 New Hampshire had directed in state statute that town clerks be chosen by ballot. Ballots were hand written, although by the 1830s, printed ballots came into use.</p>
            <p>Early in the new republic, the right to vote reflected the tension between the Federalists, those property owners with a "stake in society," and the Republicans (Democratic-Republicans), who wanted to expand democratic participation as broadly as possible—so broadly, in fact, that some feared "mob rule" at the other end of the spectrum. By 1800 New Hampshire was one of just three states (the others were Kentucky and Vermont) that had universal white manhood suffrage, having done away with the requirement of property ownership. All of New England except Connecticut allowed African Americans to vote without significant restriction. New Hampshire endorsed the principle that the more people taking part in the democratic process, the better. This engaged political culture continues to this day, with high voter participation in New Hampshire's well-known first-in-the-nation presidential primary.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Daniell, Jere R.  1981. <title>Colonial New Hampshire—A History.</title>  Millwood, NY: KTO Press.</li> 
                <li>Gardner, William M., Mevers, Frank C., Upton, Richard F.  1989.  <title>New Hampshire: The State That Made Us A Nation.</title>  Portsmouth, NH:  Peter E. Randall Publisher.    </li>
                <li>Turner, Lynn Warren. 1983.  <title>The Ninth State:  New Hampshire’s Formative Years.</title>   Chapel Hill:  University of North Carolina Press.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="New Jersey">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Rosemarie Zagarri<br/>
                George Mason University
            </div>
            <p>Following orders from the Continental Congress, the New Jersey Provincial Congress devised a new framework of government for the state. Passed in July 1776, the new state constitution remained in force until 1844. Providing for annual elections, the constitution established an upper house called the Legislative Council and a lower house called the General Assembly. A joint meeting of the Council and the Assembly elected the governor. Essentially a figurehead, the governor lacked the power to veto laws passed by the legislature, could not pardon criminals, and did not have the authority to appoint individuals to state offices. These powers devolved on the legislature, which was thought to best represent the voice of the people. The governor and Legislative Council, meeting together, acted as the state's supreme court and court of appeals.</p>
            <p>Different counties in New Jersey initially used different methods of voting, some favoring viva voce voting and others the paper ballot system. After 1797, however, all the counties shifted to the secret ballot. Representation was apportioned according to geographic units; each of the state's thirteen counties elected one councilor and three assemblymen to the legislature. The constitution included a provision that allowed the legislature to "add to or diminish the number or proportion" of representatives if "a majority of representatives" deemed it "equitable and proper." Although a few slight adjustments were made in 1804, 1815, and 1818, the state did not in this period fully accept the principle that representation should be proportionate to population. In addition, officeholders had to own a certain amount of property. Members of the lower house had to possess real or personal property of at least &#163;500 in value, and members of the upper house had to own property valued at twice that much.</p>
            <p>New Jersey's suffrage laws were unique. Under the 1776 constitution, any adult inhabitant who possessed real or personal property valued at &#163;50 or more was entitled to vote. Laws passed in 1790 and 1797 made it clear that the legislators intended the constitution to enfranchise both unmarried women (single and widowed) and free blacks who met the property requirement. Although a few other states during this period did allow free blacks to vote, no other state allowed women to cast ballots. Ongoing hostility, however, resulted in the law's repeal. In 1807 the legislature eliminated all property qualifications for voting but confined the vote to white males. Thus the franchise was extended to all adult white male taxpayers at the same time that women and free blacks lost the right to vote.</p>
            <p>The 1807 law represented a rare show of bipartisan cooperation between Federalists and Republicans. Long-standing differences between East Jersey, which was primarily Presbyterian in religion and looked to New York City for its cues, and West Jersey, which was predominantly Quaker in religion and took Philadelphia as it model, had persisted from the colonial era. After the factions united to ratify the United States Constitution on December 19, 1788, the old divisions between East and West Jersey resurfaced. Counties in the southern part of the state formed the West Jersey "Junto," which tended to support Federalist policies and candidates, while East Jersey increasingly gravitated toward the emerging Democratic-Republican Party.</p>        
            <p>Throughout the 1790s, the parties battled for control. In 1798 voters reacted against the Alien and Sedition Acts by electing three Republican members out of five to represent the state in the U.S. House of Representatives. Despite Federalists' subsequent attempts to gerrymander districts to their advantage, the Republican surge continued. After 1800, New Jersey Republicans gained control of the state legislature, the governorship, and the congressional delegation. With only a brief Federalist interlude during the War of 1812, the Republicans’ dominance continued unabated until the fracture of the Republican Party itself during the Jacksonian era.</p>
            <p>Republican domination was enhanced by the state's method of electing members to Congress. Whereas most state legislatures divided their state into districts and allowed each district to select its own representative to Congress, after 1813 New Jersey chose to use the at-large method of electing congressmen. Voters throughout the state cast ballots for all the eligible candidates. The candidates with the highest totals were elected. As Republicans well knew, this system tended to result in the election of members from the majority party and to eliminate the possibility of representation for the Federalist minority. Thus both persuasion and procedural tactics enabled the New Jersey Republicans solidify their own power while eradicating the divisive legacy of the state’s colonial past.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Fleming, Thomas. <title>New Jersey: A Bicentennial History</title> (New York: Norton, 1977).</li>
                <li>Fee, Walter R. <title>The Transition from Aristocracy to Democracy in New Jersey, 1789–1829.</title> Somerville, NJ: Somerset Press, 1933.</li>
                <li>Klinghoffer, Judith Apter and Lois Elkis. <title>"'The Petticoat Electors': Women's Suffrage in New Jersey, 1776–1807,"</title> Journal of the Early Republic, 12 (Summer 1992), 169–193.</li>
                <li>Kruman, Marc W. <title>Between Authority and Liberty: State Constitution Making in Revolutionary America.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1997.</li>
                <li>McCormick, Richard P. <title>Experiment in Independence: New Jersey in the Critical Period, 1781–1789.</title> New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 1950).</li>
                <li>Zagarri, Rosemarie. <title>The Politics of Size: Representation in the United States, 1776–1850.</title> Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1987).</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="New York">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Reeve Huston<br/>
                Duke University
            </div>       
            <p>New York exerted tremendous influence in the politics of the early republic. Along with Pennsylvania, it was a battleground state, and competition bred innovation. During the 1790s, partisan activists in New York (like those in Pennsylvania) pioneered methods of popular partisan mobilization. After 1820, Empire state pols created the model of the party as a disciplined peacetime army, focused on winning and keeping political power.</p>
            <p>The state constitution of 1777 divided state government between a governor with a three-year term, a Senate with staggered four-year terms, and an Assembly that was elected every year. A Council of Revision (consisting of the governor, the chancellor, and the judges of the supreme court) held the power to veto legislation. The governor and both houses of the legislature were elected, along with a lieutenant governor and town clerks, supervisors, assessors, constables, and collectors. All other offices were appointive—most of them by the governor and/or a Council of Appointment, which consisted of the governor and four senators. The constitutional language on appointments was contradictory and a source of fierce partisan conflict. Until 1793 the governor made appointments with the advice and consent of the Council of Appointment; after that date, the Council assumed a "concurrent right" to nominate officers. Adult male freeholders who owned real and personal property worth at least £20 and tenant farmers who paid at least 40 shillings in rent, along with the freemen of Albany and New York, could vote for members of the Assembly. Electing the governor and senators was limited to adult males worth £100. Voting was by paper ballot, but in some areas the political "friends" of great men handed voters colored or intricately folded ballots and watched them deposit those ballots to ensure that they voted properly!</p>
            <p> Within this institutional framework, New York political leaders forged a fiercely competitive politics. By 1787, two clear partisan groupings had emerged in state politics: the Federalists, led by Alexander Hamilton, and the followers of Governor George Clinton. While the former practiced an elitist politics, the latter appealed to the egalitarian yearnings of middling and poor constituents and, by 1800, allied themselves with the national Republican Party. The two parties were evenly matched during the 1790s, when Republicans pioneered techniques of mass political mobilizations: electoral rallies and parades, printed ballots, partisan newspapers and handbills, door-to-door canvassing. Republicans won a commanding majority in state government in 1800 and then quickly split into three competing factions, each centered on a single leader and held together by personal loyalty and patronage: the Clintonians, increasingly led by George Clinton's nephew De Witt; the Burrites, led by Aaron Burr; and the Livingston family.  </p>
            <p>These factions' squabbling spilled over into the electoral arena with alarming regularity. In 1804, the Burrites broke from the party, running Aaron Burr for governor against the candidate of the Clinton and Livingston factions. The following year, the Clintonians staged a revolt against Governor Morgan Lewis, head of the Livingston faction, and appealed to the Burrites for an alliance. This move split the Burrites, with opponents of the alliance taking the name Martling Men. For their part, the Livingston faction, known as the Quids, forged an alliance with the Federalists. The Clintonians trounced the Quids in the 1807 gubernatorial election, bringing rival tickets (but not internectine struggles) to an end—for a while. In 1812 the Republicans nominated De Witt Clinton for governor, a move that inspired the Burrites to run their own candidate. This ever-shifting factional dance gave New York politicians a well-earned reputation for intrigue. Oliver Wolcott, a New Englander who relocated to the state, wrote that "after living a dozen years in New York, I don't pretend to comprehend their politics. It is a labyrinth of wheels within wheels, and it is understood only by the managers."</p>
            <p>The years immediately following the War of 1812 brought important changes to this factional mess. The Livingstons and Burrites lost power. The Federalists, discredited by their behavior during the war, disbanded in 1820. The Bucktails, led by Martin Van Buren, emerged as the sole challengers to the Clintonians. In some respects, the Bucktails were just like the factions they replaced, frequently forging new alliances and changing their policies for tactical advantage. But in important ways they were different. Led by upwardly mobile men of middling origin, they explicitly rejected the personalist politics that had dominated New York since before the Revolution. Rather than basing political allegiances on personal loyalty and patronage, Van Buren envisioned parties as embodiments of competing social interests, held together by principle and policy. Although the Bucktails did not hew to consistent policies or principles until the early 1830s, they did become a disciplined political machine. Activists united behind party candidates and policies, on pain of losing office; Bucktail newspapers and activists propagated a single, clear partisan message. Van Buren's faction gained control of state government in 1820. So effective were the Bucktails in retaining power that their Clintonian enemies dubbed them the Albany Regency.</p>
            <p>The Bucktails also proved the champions of a widened popular participation in politics. They dominated the 1821 state constitutional convention, which dramatically expanded the suffrage, increased the number of elective posts, and abolished constitutional checks on the power of elected officials. The new constitution eliminated the Council of Revision, empowering the governor with the legislative veto. It abolished the Council of Appointment, transferring the selection of sheriffs, county clerks, and coroners to the voters, while leaving the election of most state officials in the hands of the legislature. And it eliminated the property qualification for the vote among white men. Beginning in 1822, any white adult male who paid state or county taxes, worked on the public roads, or served in the militia could vote for all elective officers. African American males, however, faced a $250 property qualification for the suffrage.</p>
            <p>The Bucktails dominated state politics after 1820. Only in 1824 did the Clintonians, now dubbing themselves the "People's Men," win the governorship and a majority in the legislature. The next year, both factions, shaken by John Quincy Adams's ascension to the presidency, made an alliance behind the presidential ambitions of Andrew Jackson. By 1828 the state's factional conflict turned on national allegiances, with a Jacksonian party opposed by Adams men (also known as National Republicans). The political conflicts of the 1820s led both Clintonians and Bucktails to revive many of the old techniques of popular mobilization pioneered in the 1790s—and to increase their effectiveness through an unprecedented degree of discipline among party cadre. When Martin Van Buren became Andrew Jackson's campaign manager in 1828, the Bucktails' methods and organization provided the core model on which national party politics was built.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Alexander, DeAlva Stanwood. <title>Political History of the State of New York. 3 vols.</title> New York: Henry Holt, 1909).</li>
                <li>Benson, Lee. <title>The Concept of Jacksonian Democracy: New York as a Test Case, 1961</title>; reprint ed. New York: Atheneum, 1964).</li>
                <li>Brooke, John L. <title>Columbia Rising: Civil Life on the Upper Hudson from the Revolution to the Age of Jackson.</title>Chapeh Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2014.</li>
                <li>Cole, Donald B. <title>Martin Van Buren and the American Political System.</title> Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1984.</li>
                <li>Countryman, Edward. <title>"From Revolution to Statehood."</title> In Milton M. Klein, ed., <title>The Empire State: A History of New York.</title> Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 2001, pp. 229–301.</li>
                <li>Huston, Reeve. <title>Land and Freedom: Rural Society, Popular Protest, and Party Politics in Antebellum New York.</title> New York: Oxford University Press, 2000.</li>  
                <li>Taylor, Alan. <title>William Cooper’s Town: Power and Persuasion on the Frontier of the Early American Republic.</title> New York: Knopf, 1995.</li>
                <li>Young, Alfred F. <title>The Democratic-Republicans of New York: The Origins, 1763–1797.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1987.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="North Carolina">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Kevin T. Barksdale<br/>
                Marshall University
            </div>  
            <p>Established in 1663, the proprietary colony of Carolina became the state of North Carolina during the American Revolution. In December of 1776, the North Carolina Provincial Congress ratified the state's first constitution, which established three branches of government: a bicameral General Assembly comprising a Senate and a House of Commons; a judiciary; and a weak executive. Representatives to the legislature were chosen by ballot annually, with each county electing one senator and two members to the House of Commons. Landholding, age, and residency restrictions limited the size of the electorate. The legislature appointed supreme court judges and annually elected the governor and representatives to the United States Congress.</p>
            <p> Following the Revolution, Federalists and Anti-Federalists fought for control over the state government. This "critical period" laid the foundation for the clash over ratification of the United States Constitution. North Carolina's delegation to the 1787 Constitutional Convention favored strengthening the central government, but not at the expense of individual liberties or their state's sovereignty. Anti-Federalist representatives to the state's 1788 constitutional convention blocked ratification of the Constitution, but Federalists eventually forced the convening of a second convention. On November 21, 1789, North Carolina became the twelfth state to ratify the Constitution. Anti-Federalists chipped away at Federalist dominance during the next decade and, by 1792, secured a majority in the legislature. The efforts of Federalists such as James Iredell and influential easterners allowed the party to continue to elect candidates to the United States Congress and the governorship, but by 1799, distrust of the central government and growing resentment over the Federalist Party's alliance with the state's eastern elite led to the party's demise.</p>
            <p> Swept into power by their platform of state hegemony, strict constitutional construction, tax restraint, and the promotion of smallholder interests, Republicans controlled the state's political future. Republicans confronted a series of problems that included currency inflation, unstable banking, Amerindian resistance to western expansion, inadequate internal improvements, educational deficiencies, economic stagnation, and an undemocratic political system. Despite the progressive efforts of Orange County’s Senator Archibald Murphey, resistance from the state's conservatives and easterners derailed proposed reforms. Despite state Republican support for Jefferson's acquisition of Louisiana Territory and for "Mr. Madison's War," North Carolina increasingly found itself isolated from the rest of the nation, earning the moniker the "Rip Van Winkle State."</p>
            <p>The 1820s proved to be a transformative period as divisions emerged within the Republican ranks and a wave of democratization swept the state in the wake of Andrew Jackson's rise to prominence. The Missouri Compromise further fractured the Republican Party, and the 1824 presidential election cemented the state's political realignment. Republican leaders nominated William H. Crawford, alienating many Republicans. That decision led to the formation of a splinter party whose "People's Ticket" nominated Jackson for president and John C. Calhoun for vice president. Jackson won the popular vote in North Carolina, but the state's electoral votes went to Crawford. The 1824 election loosened the political grip of the eastern elite, and the continued political democratization propelled Jackson to victory in the 1828 election.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Broussard, James H. <title>"The North Carolina Federalists, 1800–1816."</title> North Carolina Historical Review, 55 (1978): 18–41.</li>
                <li>Butler, Lindley S. and Alan D. Watson, eds. <title>The North Carolina Experience: An Interpretive and Documentary History.</title> Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1984.</li>
                <li>Cavanagh, John C. <title>Decision at Fayetteville: The North Carolina Ratification Convention and the General Assembly of 1789.</title> Raleigh, NC: Division of Archives and History, 1989.</li>
                <li>Gilpatrick, Delbert H. <title>Jeffersonian Democracy in North Carolina, 1789–1816.</title> New York: Octagon Books, 1967.</li>
                <li>Jeffrey, Thomas E. <title>State Parties and National Politics: North Carolina, 1815–1861.</title> Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1989.</li>  
                <li>Lefler, Hugh Talmage and Albert Ray Newsome. <title>North Carolina: A History of a Southern State, 3rd ed.</title> Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1973.</li>
                <li>Powell, William S. <title>North Carolina: Through Four Centuries.</title> Chapel Hill: The University of North Carolina Press, 1989.</li>
                <li>Risjord, Norman K. <title>Chesapeake Politics, 1781–1800.</title> New York: Columbia University Press, 1978.</li>
                <li>Trenholme, Louise Irby. <title>The Ratification of the Federal Constitution in North Carolina.</title> New York: Columbia University Press, 1932.</li>
                <li>Wheeler, John Hill. <title>Historical Sketches of North Carolina: from 1584 to 1851, compiled from original records, official documents and traditional statements ; with biographical sketches of her distinguished statemen, jurists, lawyers, soldiers, divines, etc.</title> Philadelphia, PA: Lippincott, Grambo and Co., 1851. </li>
                <li><a href="http://www.northcarolinahistory.org/">North Carolina History Project </a></li>
                <li><a href="http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/states/nc07.htm">1776 North Carolina Constitution</a>The Avalon Project at Yale Law School</li> 
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Northwest Territory">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Philip Lampi<br/>
            </div>    
            <p>"Part of the vast domain ceded by Great Britain to the United States in the Treaty of Paris (1783), the Northwest Territory encompassed the area west of Pennsylvania, east of the Mississippi River, and north of the Ohio River to the border with British Canada.  The 'Old Northwest,' as the region later came to be known, eventually included the states of Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Michigan, Wisconsin, and the part of Minnesota east of the Mississippi River.  The creation of the Northwest Territory was first implied in the Articles of Confederation (1780), which stipulated that all lands beyond the bounds of the original thirteen states would be owned and administrated by the national government.</p>
            <p>"Although some form of territorial governance continued in the Old Northwest until Minnesota achieved statehood in 1858, the administrative history of the Northwest Territory is fairly brief.  The celebrated revolutionary war general Arthur St. Clair establish the first territorial government on 15 July 1788.  Because of increased migration, Congress in 1800 divided the Northwest Territory for administrative purposes and designed the western portion as the territory of Indiana.  The reduced Northwest Territory ceased to exist as an official geopolitical entity in 1803, when the state of Ohio was admitted to the Union and Congress designated the region to the north as the territory of Michigan."  from the Dictionary of American History, 3rd ed, Volume 6.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <title></title>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Ohio">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Donald J. Ratcliffe<br/>
                University of Oxford, England
            </div>    
            <p>
                In these years, Ohio changed from a virtually unpeopled frontier area within the Northwest Territory to the fourth most powerful state in federal elections. Its first significant elections were for the lower house of the Territorial Assembly in December 1798. Suffrage was restricted to adult males who owned fifty acres freehold (the most limited franchise in the nation), although Governor Arthur St. Clair extended the vote to those who owned town lots of comparable value. Voting took place viva voce at the county seat, under the supervision of men appointed by the governor, who also determined apportionment and could veto legislation and prorogue (postpone) and dissolve the Assembly. The upper house, the Council, was appointed by the president from a list of names drawn up by the house; Congress appointed the governor on the president's nomination. This authoritarian system was overthrown when Congress passed the Enabling Act of 1802, authorizing the calling of a convention elected virtually on the basis of manhood suffrage.</p>
            <p>Ohio became a state in March 1803, operating under the constitution drafted in November 1802. That instrument gave little power or patronage, and no veto, to the governor, who was elected biennially. The all-powerful General Assembly was divided into two chambers: The House was elected annually by county constituencies, and the Senate was elected biennially, half the members each year, in districts made up of one or more counties. There were no property qualifications for membership in the Assembly. Every four years the state took a census of adult males and redistributed legislative seats, and congressional districts were reapportioned each decade immediately after Congress had reapportioned the federal House and electoral college. Beginning with the first presidential election in 1804, the electors were chosen by statewide popular vote. The right to vote was limited to white adult males who had been resident for one year and had paid a tax. However, because the state constitution defined compulsory work on the roads as a tax and all adult males between the ages of 18 and 55 were obliged to work on the roads (or buy a substitute), this amounted to a nearly all-inclusive franchise for white males. From the start, voting was by secret ballot, with ballots deposited in special locked boxes, and whereas under the territory, voters had had to travel to the few county seats to vote, people now voted at a central place in each of the rapidly multiplying townships.  </p>
            <p>This democratic electoral system produced elections that saw a surprising degree of partisan action and comparatively high—but fluctuating—voter involvement, especially after 1807 when the key elections began to coincide in even years. The Federalist predominance of the territorial period was overthrown in 1802—1803, and the then overwhelmingly dominant Democratic-Republican party soon divided along factional lines, notably over the role of the judiciary. In some parts of the state, the Federalist Party revived after 1807 but suffered a severe decline after 1816. As a consequence, nonpartisan elections became even more common, although old-party considerations operated in some local elections into the 1820s. In 1824 Ohio's first competitive election for the presidency saw turnout surge as voters began giving their allegiance to entirely new political formations.    
            </p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <title></title>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li><title>Annual Report of the Secretary of the State to the Governor of the State of Ohio: including the statistical report to the general assembly for the year 1875.</title> Colombus, OH: Nevins &amp; Myers, State Printers, 1876. (Lists members of the General Assembly and their districts from the formation of the state)</li>
                <li>Brown, Jeffrey P. and Andrew R. L. Cayton, eds. <title>The Pursuit of Public Power: Political Culture in Ohio, 1787–1861.</title> Kent, OH: Kent State University Press, 1994.</li>
                <li>Cayton, Andrew R. L. <title>The Frontier State: Ideology and Politics in the Ohio Country.</title> Kent, OH: Kent State University Press, 1986.</li>
                <li>Ohio Historical Society, Ohio Fundamental Documents Searchable Database, <br/>
                    http://www.ohiohistory.org/resource/database/funddocs.html </li>
                <li>Ratcliffe, Donald J. <title>"Voter Turnout in Early Ohio,"</title> Journal of the Early Republic, 7 (1987): 223–251. Reprinted in New Perspectives on the Early Republic, ed. Ralph D. Gray and Michael A. Morrison. Urbana and Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1994, pp. 269–297.</li>
                <li>________. <title>"The Mystery of Ohio's Missing Presidential Election Returns, 1804–1848,"</title> Archival Issues: The Journal of the Midwest Archives Conference, 17(2)(1992): 137–144.
                </li>
                <li>________. <title>Party Spirit in a Frontier Republic: Democratic Politics in Ohio, 1793–1821.</title> Columbus, OH: Ohio State University Press, 1998.</li>
                <li>________. <title>The Politics of Long Division: The Birth of the Second Party System in Ohio, 1818–1828.</title> Columbus: Ohio State University Press, 2000.</li>
                <li>________. <title>"The Changing Political World of Thomas Worthington."</title> in <title>The Center of a Great Empire: The Ohio Country in the Early Republic</title>, ed. Andrew R. L. Cayton and Stuart D. Hobbs. Athens: Ohio University Press, 2005, pp. 36–61.</li>
                <li>Utter, William T. <title>The Frontier State, 1803–1825</title>, 1943 reprint ed. Columbus: Ohio Historical Society, 1968), Vol. 2 of Carl Wittke, ed., A History of the State of Ohio, 6 vols. Columbus: Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society, 1941–1944.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Orleans Territory">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Philip Lampi<br/>
            </div>    
            <p>The acquisition of a large area of land from France, that became known as the Louisiana Purchase, and which doubled the size of the United States, was formalized on December 20, 1803.</p>
            <p>On March 26, 1804 Congress passed the Organic Act, which was to be implemented on October 1, 1804. This act organized the land within the Louisiana Purchase that was south of the 33 parallel as the Territory of Orleans, also known as Orleans Territory. The remainder of the Purchase became the unorganized District of Louisiana and after Louisiana became a state in 1812, it was renamed the Missouri Territory. In 1810 the United States annexed part of West Florida from Spain, some of which became part of Orleans Territory and later the state of Louisiana.  The lower western area around the Red River remained in dispute with Spain until a permanent boundary was settled in 1819.</p>
            <p>A Territorial Governor and Secretary along with Judges of a Superior Court were appointed either by the President or Congress, and a District Court for Orleans Territory was also created. The first and only Territorial Governor was William C. C. Claiborne.</p>
            <p>The Territory was also entitled to a Delegate in Congress, who was elected by the Territorial Legislature. Daniel Clark, the first Delegate chosen took his seat on December 1, 1806. It appears the only governing officials chosen by popular vote were members of the Territorial Legislature.</p>
            <p>The Territorial legislature on April 10, 1805 created twelve counties, but in 1807 they replaced this system with the establishment of nineteen civil parishes, which reflected the government under previous French and Spanish rule.  The parishes supplanted the counties and became the basic unit of government.</p>
            <p>On February 20, 1811 Congress passed an Act for the process of allowing the Orleans Territory to become a state.  This Act was submitted by Governor Claiborne to the territorial legislature, which on April 24, 1811 approved legislation for holding elections for delegates and also the convening of a Constitutional Convention. The elections for delegates were scheduled for the third Monday in September, and the Convention was to meet in New Orleans on the third Monday in November.</p>
            <p>The Constitutional Convention which met in New Orleans was comprised of 17 American and 23 Creoles. The Constitution adopted by this Convention was submitted to Congress on January 23, 1812. It was approved by Congress and President James Madison in early April, with the official date of admission being set as April 30, 1812.  This marked the end of the Orleans Territory, and as the new state had taken the name of Louisiana, the unorganized territory with that name was then changed to Missouri.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Pennsylvania">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Jeffrey L. Pasley<br/>
                University of Missouri
            </div>      
            <p>Although it generally disappears from the narratives of American history once the seat of national government departs Philadelphia in 1800, Pennsylvania was quite simply the ground floor of American democracy. The Keystone State produced no Jeffersons or Adamses, and its only president (James Buchanan) ranks comfortably in the bottom three, but this was the state where democratic politics, American-style, was invented. Given that Pennsylvania had early America's least stratified, most ethnically diverse electorate and most consistently liberal suffrage requirements, it should come as no surprise that such long-term features of American democracy as the political party, the presidential campaign, the nominating convention, and the partisan newspaper all started here.   
            </p>
            <p>Pennsylvania's fractious political history begins with the conflict over the state's ultraradical constitution of 1776. Written under the direct influence of Thomas Paine and the plebeian and middle-class militiamen who spearheaded Pennsylvania's belated independence movement, the 1776 constitution dispensed with the classical republican ideal of "mixed government" and vested nearly all power in a unicameral assembly elected under conditions of almost universal white manhood suffrage. That is, all "freemen" aged twenty-one or older who paid taxes or whose father paid taxes could vote and hold office. The legislature was constitutionally required to meet with its doors open to the public at all times. There was no upper house to check the people's annually elected representatives, and a chief executive called the president was elected by the legislature and had no veto power. The constitution would be enforced not by unelected judges but, rather, by a popularly elected Council of Censors that would convene to revise the constitution every seven years. 
            </p>
            <p>Bitter divisions over the constitution of 1776 and its radically democratic ideals defined the first party battle in Pennsylvania state politics and formed the backdrop for all further developments, as Philadelphia radicals and their rural allies tried to keep the state's uniquely democratic and egalitarian revolutionary legacy alive and others tried to curb or squelch it. No one dared to attack democracy or equality in principle, but many of Philadelphia's most prominent and erudite men, including Dr. Benjamin Rush, Judge James Wilson, and Chief Justice Thomas McKean, became harsh detractors of the 1776 constitution, pushing for a more conservative and conventional government with a bicameral legislature, a stronger executive, and a more independent judiciary. After more than a decade of opposition, these so-called Republicans finally succeeded in getting the new state constitution they wanted in 1790; many were also strong supporters of the new, less democratic federal Constitution that was written in Philadelphia. The radicals who defended the original document were known as Constitutionalists, a confusing appellation because many Pennsylvania Constitutionalists leaned against the generally antidemocratic federal Constitution.</p>
            <p>The 1790 constitution created an assembly with annual terms and a state Senate whose members were elected to four-year terms. The old state "presidency" was replaced with a governor who was elected by the people every three years and had both the authority to veto legislation and the power to appoint an extensive array of state and county officials, right down to local recorders of deeds and justices of the peace. Judges in the expanded state court system were appointed by the governor and served for life ("during good behavior"). Although many Constitutionalists continued to prefer the old system, conflicts over the state government died down during the nine-year governorship of Thomas Mifflin, a popular war hero generally supported by all factions. Increasingly, over Mifflin's term, the real power accumulated in the hands of his right-hand man, Secretary of the Commonwealth Alexander J. Dallas, an ambitious lawyer recently emigrated from Jamaica.</p>
            <p> Dallas was deeply involved in the emergence of the new political division that emerged in the 1790s, this time stemming from Philadelphia's status as the seat of national government. The "national" political controversies that broke out in the Cabinet and the Congress between Thomas Jefferson, Alexander Hamilton, and their followers were also local ones in Philadelphia as they spilled out into the streets and the press. The nascent national political parties (the Federalists who supported Hamilton's policies and thought of themselves more as friends of the government than as a party per se, and the Jeffersonian opposition who usually referred to themselves as Republicans but were often referred to by their enemies as "democrats or "Jacobins") battled over Philadelphia's Bank of the United States and fought for public approbation through Philadelphia newspapers that circulated nationally. When Citizen Edmond Genêt arrived and sparked the formation of the Democratic-Republican Societies, Philadelphia had the largest and most active ones.</p>    
            <p>As the epicenter of national political conflict, Philadelphia, followed by the rest of the state, led the nation in the development of party politics. Republican John Swanwick won one of the first clearly party-contested congressional elections in 1794, and a coterie of Philadelphians led by Clerk of the House of Representatives John Beckley and the Aurora newspaper mounted the first serious popular presidential campaign, for Thomas Jefferson, in 1796, carrying the state and almost the election for the opposition leader.</p>
            <p>The Jeffersonian Republicans finally took power in the state in 1799, when Chief Justice McKean beat Federalist James Ross of Pittsburgh in the race to succeed Mifflin. A key factor in McKean's victory was the swing of many German Lutheran voters away from the Federalists in the wake of the offensive Direct Tax of 1798 (called the "Window Tax" for the one of the methods that assessors used to determine a taxpayer's wealth) and the overzealous, xenophobic suppression of Fries's Rebellion in the German areas of eastern Pennsylvania.</p>
            <p>The Federalists remained competitive in certain areas of the state (especially the southeast) through the 1820s, but after 1799 they were reduced to playing spoiler or kingmaker in statewide elections. In 1800, Federalists in the state Senate prevented Pennsylvania from holding a popular presidential election at all, so certain were they of losing again. Luckily for the Federalists, the majority Republicans (increasingly either adding "Democratic" to their name after 1800 or switching to "Democrat") were plagued by factionalism. The old divide between Constitutionalists and Republicans reemerged with a vengeance after 1802, as radicals led by Aurora editor and Irish political refugee William Duane and Congressman Michael Leib clashed with McKean over impeachments and reforms of the court system and constitution designed to help more litigants avoid the need to hire lawyers, make judges more democratically accountable, and reduce the governor's appointment powers. McKean's vetoes of the reform legislation and his widely reported remarks about the "clodpoles and ignoramuses" who supported the reforms led to an 1805 reelection challenge by Speaker of the House Simon Snyder, a German of rural working-class roots who became the state's most popular political figure in the early nineteenth century. McKean barely won the 1805 election, but only by gaining support from Federalists and a breakaway faction of so-called "Constitutional Republicans." They were led by Alexander Dallas and consisted mostly of wealthier men, attorneys, and officeholders grown conservative in power and restive under the "tyranny of printers" such as Duane. The Aurora labeled the schismatics Quids, meaning "a hermaphrodite thing, partaking of two characters, and yet having neither!"</p>     
            <p>In 1808, all the Republicans united behind Snyder, who trounced James Ross in a campaign managed by Snyder's friend, editor John Binns of the Democratic Press, an immigrant radical like Duane but much more ideologically flexible. Relations cooled quickly between Duane's Philadelphia radicals and the more rural Snyderites, amid disagreements over the Republican establishment's increasing enthusiasm for banks and other economic development schemes that "Old School" Democrats such as Duane considered corrupt unless tightly controlled. The "New School" of Binns's Snyderites, allied with Dallas's Quids, dominated the state during most of the War of 1812 era and won recognition from the James Madison administration as the regular Democratic-Republican organization in Pennsylvania. The Old School men even cooperated with certain Federalists for a time in efforts to replace Madison with De Witt Clinton in the presidential election of 1812. Trying to break the New School's stranglehold on offices and patronage, Duane's Old School repeatedly challenged the prevailing legislative caucus system of nominating candidates for high office. The caucus was especially aberrant in Pennsylvania, where local public meetings had been the major form of party nominations since the 1790s.</p>
            <p>The Old School Democrats' anti-caucus campaign finally met with some success after the War of 1812 during the misnamed Era of Good Feeling. A group of Old School men and disaffected Federalists meeting as "Independent Republicans" held Pennsylvania's first two-party conventions at Carlisle in 1816 and 1817 and nominated Joseph Hiester, who narrowly lost to the New School's man William Findlay, state treasurer under Snyder but a creature of the state's burgeoning business interests. Financial scandals in Findlay's administration, together with the Panic of 1819, enabled the Old School to run Hiester successfully in 1820. Thanks to a generational turnover in leadership, the regular, New School Democrats were increasingly known as the "Family" party after the three Philadelphia brothers-in-law who were its leaders: Postmaster Richard Bache, leading attorney Thomas Sergeant, and Alexander Dallas's son, future Vice President George Mifflin Dallas.</p>
            <p>Left leaderless by Hiester's distaste for party politicking and Duane's financial collapse, the remnants of the Old School (including Duane's son and other Aurora veterans) could not prevent the Family's return to power in 1823. Yet that same year, they were crucial to the surprise launch of Andrew Jackson's presidential candidacy by a political convention in Harrisburg that upset the Family's plan to throw the state behind John C. Calhoun. The next decade saw a vicious factional battle for the mantle of Pennsylvania Jacksonianism that the Family, or "Eleventh-Hour Men," eventually won.</p> 
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Baumann, Roland M. <title>"John Swanwick: Spokesman for 'Merchant Republicanism' in Philadelphia, 1790–98."</title> Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 97 (April 1973): 131–182.</li>
                <li>Brunhouse, Robert L. <title>The Counter-Revolution in Pennsylvania, 1776–1790.</title> Harrisburg: Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1971.</li>
                <li>Ferguson, Robert J. <title>Early Western Pennsylvania Politics.</title> Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1938.</li>
                <li>Higginbotham, Sanford W. <title>The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800–1816.</title> Harrisburg: Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1952.</li>
                <li>Kehl, James A. <title>Ill Feeling in the Era of Good Feeling: Western Pennsylvania Political Battles, 1815–1825.</title> Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1956.</li>
                <li>Keller, Kenneth W. <title>"Cultural Conflict in Early Nineteenth-Century Pennsylvania Politics."</title> Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 110 (1986): 509–530.</li>
                <li>Klein, Philip Shriver. <title>Pennsylvania Politics, 1817–1832: A Game Without Rules.</title> Philadelphia: Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1940.</li>
                <li>Koschnik, Albrecht. <title>"The Democratic Societies of Philadelphia and the Limits of the American Public Sphere, Circa 1793–1795."</title> William and Mary Quarterly, 3rd series 58(3) (July 2001): 615–636.</li>
                <li>Miller, Randall M. and William Pencak, eds. <title>Pennsylvania: A History of the Commonwealth.</title> University Park and Harrisburg: Pennsylvania State University Press and Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 2002. (Columbus: Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society, 1941-44).</li>
                <li>Newman, Paul Douglas. <title>Fries's Rebellion: The Enduring Struggle for the American Revolution.</title> Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2004.</li>
                <li>Pasley, Jeffrey L. <title>"'A Journeyman, Either in Law or Politics': John Beckley and the Social Origins of Political Campaigning."</title> Journal of the Early Republic, 16(4) (Winter 1996): 531–569.</li>
                <li>Pasley, Jeffrey L. <title>"The Tyranny of Printers": Newspaper Politics in the Early American Republic.</title> Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 2001.</li>
                <li>Phillips, Kim T. <title>"Democrats of the Old School in the Era of Good Feelings."</title> Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 95 (July 1971): 363–382.</li>
                <li>________. <title>"The Pennsylvania Origins of the Jackson Movement."</title> Political Science Quarterly, 91(3) (Fall 1976): 489–508.</li>
                <li>________. <title>"William Duane, Philadelphia's Democratic Republicans, and the Origins of Modern Politics."</title> Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography 101 (1977): 365–387.</li>
                <li>Phillips, Kim Tousley. <title>"William Duane, Revolutionary Editor."</title> Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Berkeley, 1968.</li>
                <li>Sapio, Victor A. <title>Pennsylvania and the War of 1812.</title> Lexington: University Press of Kentucky, 1970.</li>
                <li>Shankman, Andrew. <title>Crucible of American Democracy: The Struggle to Fuse Egalitarianism and Capitalism in Jeffersonian Pennsylvania.</title> Lawrence: University Press of Kansas, 2004.</li>
                <li>Slaughter, Thomas P. <title>The Whiskey Rebellion: Frontier Epilogue to the American Revolution.</title> New York: Oxford University Press, 1986.</li>
                <li>Tagg, James D. <title>Benjamin Franklin Bache and the Philadelphia "Aurora."</title> Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1991.</li>
                <li>Tinkcom, Harry Marlin. <title>The Republicans and the Federalists in Pennsylvania, 1790–1801: A Study in National Stimulus and Local Response.</title> Harrisburg: Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1950.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Rhode Island">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Andrew Robertson<br/>
                City University of New York
            </div>
            <p>Rhode Island is the smallest state with the longest name. Its official name, "The State of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations," gives evidence of the divisions that have beset the state since its foundation. Although Rhode Island was established as a refuge from the Puritan orthodoxy of Massachusetts Bay, its earliest settlers found it no easier to get along with each other than they had with the authorities in Boston. In 1636 Roger Williams, exiled from Massachusetts, founded a settlement at the head of Narragansett Bay that he called Providence; in 1638 Anne and William Hutchinson and William Coddington settled on Aquidneck Island (later "Rhode Island") in Portsmouth. Several years later, Coddington quarreled with the Hutchinsons and founded Newport, a few miles to the south.</p>
            <p>In 1643 the colonists put their differences aside and united in their support of Roger Williams's voyage to England, during which he secured a patent for the colony. In 1663 that document was superseded by a royal charter granted by Charles II, which guaranteed extensive religious toleration and provided the framework of government that would last long beyond the American Revolution, until 1843. The Rhode Island charter was the supreme law of the state for 180 years (the U.S. Constitution has been in effect only a few years more than that; it is now 220 years old).</p>
            <p>The Rhode Island charter was easily the most democratic framework of government in any colony in the seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries. After the Revolution, and especially in the 1790s, however, the framework of government began to show signs of obsolescence. Perhaps the worst aspect of Rhode Island's charter government was the malapportionment of its legislature, which was already acute at the time Rhode Island belatedly ratified the Constitution, in 1790. In that same year, Rhode Island fatefully launched the American industrial revolution at Slater's Mill in Pawtucket, and the economy and population of the towns near Providence took off. As a consequence, the malapportionment grew far worse.</p>
            <p>While Providence and Pawtucket were booming, Newport and southern Rhode Island were declining. Although Newport had been a thriving commercial center before the Revolution, the long British naval occupation during the war and the decline in the rum, molasses, and slave trades in the 1790s brought a relative decline in Newport's fortunes. The inland Rhode Island towns west of Narragansett Bay did not share in the growth of Providence or even in the relative stability of Newport.</p>
            <p>The four founding towns of Rhode Island (Providence, Newport, Portsmouth, and Warwick) were given the largest share of representatives in the legislative assembly: four seats each. Newer towns were given two seats. The state senate was elected by the assembly, and because each county claimed equal representation in that body, the southern portion of the state had veto power in the upper house.</p>
            <p>The Charter of 1663 made no provision for the separation of powers; that is, it set up no formal division of responsibilities for the legislative, executive, and judicial functions of government. The legislature, known as the General Assembly, was the court of original jurisdiction in cases of debt and divorce, and it constituted the final court of appeal in all cases heard in Rhode Island until 1843. The governor and the legislature divided responsibilities in ways more akin to colonial government than to the new institutional frameworks being developed in other states. Although the legislature possessed substantial power, the governor nevertheless held significant patronage power in the state, and for that reason, Rhode Island organized its rough-and-tumble politics on a statewide basis long before it declared itself a state.</p>
            <p>As with many individuals who suffer from arrested development, early Rhode Island showed signs of a remarkable political precocity. In the 1740s, two nascent political parties developed around the personalities of Samuel Ward and Stephen Hopkins. The Ward faction represented Newport and the surrounding southern towns. The Hopkins faction was attuned to the interests of Providence and its environs, which was already beginning its arc of ascendance by the middle of the eighteenth century. Historian Jack Greene credits Rhode Island (along with New York) with the development of the first modern, semi-permanent political parties.</p>
            <p>Beginning in 1786, the “Country Party” of Jonathan Hazard took control of the Rhode Island government. The Country Party was committed to relief of the hard-pressed small farmers. In essence that meant a strong commitment to Rhode Island's issuance of paper currency. (In that same year, Daniel Shays and his cohorts launched a rebellion in Massachusetts to try to force that state's authorities to provide the same debt relief as Rhode Island.) Rhode Island's distressed farmers strongly resisted ratifying the federal Constitution, which prohibited the states from issuing their own currency. They were joined in their resistance by the Quakers in southern Rhode Island, who also denounced the new federal Constitution because of its implicit recognition of slavery. Through eleven attempts by the merchant interests in Providence (called the Minority Party) to gain ratification of the Constitution, the Country Party prevailed, finally acquiescing only in the face of the threat of Providence's secession from the state and the threatened enactment of tariffs by the new federal Congress against the tiny independent republic.</p>
            <p>The Federal era brought new political difficulties to the state, even as it brought further prosperity to Providence. Rhode Island, which had given birth to the earliest modern political parties in America, now saw its parties degenerate into mere patronage-grabbing personal factions, only incidentally related to the important political and ideological contests between Hamiltonian Federalists and Jeffersonian Republicans. These factions spent enormous amounts on campaigns revolving around personalities, private feuds, and outright bribery to control the elections.</p>
            <p>For the first two decades of the Constitutional era, Rhode Island was a one-party political monopoly disguised as a competitive two-party state. The political monopoly was exercised at the gubernatorial level by Arthur Fenner, who held that office unopposed from 1790 until his death in 1805. Fenner was nominally a Republican, but he had few connections with the party organization in Philadelphia and later in Washington. And although Fenner was a nominal Republican, the congressional delegation was Federalist until 1800, and the presidential electors for Rhode Island were Federalist in all presidential elections from 1792 to 1816, except for the Republican landslide in 1804. From 1807 to 1811, Arthur Fenner's son James was elected to the governorship by Federalists and some dissident Republicans on a Union ticket. Because of strong opposition to the Embargo, to Non-importation, and later to "Mr. Madison's War," Rhode Island Federalists swept to a gubernatorial victory under William Jones in 1811 and in succeeding annual elections through 1816. In 1817, Republican Nehemiah Knight won the governorship, and he ran unopposed by the Federalists except for the year 1821. James Fenner was returned to the governorship in 1824 and held that office until 1829.</p>
            <p>Colonial Rhode Islanders enjoyed one of the widest suffrages in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. At the beginning of the nineteenth century, however, Rhode Island's restricted suffrage was remarked upon as a cause of its "otherwise-minded" politics: corrupt, vindictive, and devoid of substance. The property requirement for freeholders to vote was $134. This was enough of an obstacle that in no election in Rhode Island's early republican era, from 1790 to 1824, did a majority of its adult male inhabitants vote, although the closely contested election of 1811 nearly reached the 50 percent mark. Corruption of the voting process resembled the worst practices in pre-Reform Britain, where voters were "manufactured" by fraudulent transfers of land to unpropertied voters with instructions on how to vote. The father of one candidate in Bristol manufactured mortgages on his property to ensure his son's election. In another election in the 1820s, a South County creditor referred to those white farmers in his debt as his "slaves." As the years wore on under the increasingly obsolete charter, the Rhode Island legislature became increasingly obstinate. In 1822 the legislature restricted the vote to whites only, disenfranchising the male people of color of the state, all of whom had previously been just as eligible as the white male inhabitants to vote. In the 1820s, with increasing numbers of immigrants working in Providence and Pawtucket, this one-time haven of religious refugees deliberately kept higher restrictions on immigrant voting to ensure that Providence Catholics would not gain even a modicum of political power until after the Dorr Rebellion. By 1829, 60 percent of Rhode Island's adult male inhabitants were ineligible to vote, and the number was growing.</p>
            <p>Rhode Island shared with South Carolina the dubious distinction of being one of the last two states to preserve a property requirement for adult white male voters. Like the Chartists in Britain, Rhode Island suffrage reformers faced the violent suppression of their attempts to create a constitutional order based on universal manhood suffrage. Thomas Wilson Dorr, the leader of the attempt to frame a constitution based on universal manhood suffrage, was tried and convicted of treason in 1844 and sentenced to life imprisonment (his sentence was commuted the following year). In 1844 a new constitution was approved for Rhode Island that allowed for all adult white males to vote for a poll tax of one dollar. With that grudging and still racially restrictive nod to political reality, Rhode Island’s political parties, voting, and political practices gradually came to resemble those of her New England neighbors.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Conley, Patrick T. <title>Democracy in Decline: Rhode Island's Constitutional Development, 1776–1841.</title> Providence: Rhode Island Historical Society, 1977.</li>
                <li>Coleman, Peter J. <title>The Transformation of Rhode Island, 1790–1860.</title> Providence, R.I.: Brown University Press, 1963.</li>
                <li>Gettleman, Marvin E. <title>The Dorr Rebellion: A Study in American Radicalism.</title> New York: Random House, 1973.</li>
                <li>Herndon, Ruth Wallis. <title>"Governing the Affairs of the Town: Continuity and Change in Rhode Island, 1750–1800."</title> Unpublished dissertation, American University, 1992.</li>
                <li>Lemons, J. Stanley and Michael A. McKenna. <title>"Re-Enfranchisement of Rhode Island Negroes,"</title> Rhode Island History, 30(1971): 3–13.</li>
                <li>McLoughlin, William G. <title>Rhode Island: A Bicentennial History.</title> New York: Norton, 1978.</li>
                <li>Polishook, Irwin H. <title>Rhode Island and the Union, 1774–1795.</title> Evanston, Ill.: Northwestern University Press, 1969.</li>
                <li>Sweet, John Wood. <title>"Bodies Politic: Colonialism, Race and the Emergence of the American North. Rhode Island, 1730–1830."</title> Unpublished dissertation, Princeton University, 1995.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="South Carolina">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Jonathan Mercantini, Kean University
            </div>  
            
            <p>On May 23, 1788, South Carolina became the eighth state to ratify the Federal Constitution.  Although there was considerable opposition from the backcountry region, representatives from the capital, Charleston, and the surrounding lowcountry regions prevailed.  This division in state politics would continue until a series of compromises were completed in 1808 balancing the representation of the two regions.</p>
            <p>A new state constitution was adopted by the South Carolina General Assembly in 1790.  This document preserved the weak executive structure that dated back to before the American Revolution.  For example, the governor did not possess veto power after 1790.  The governor and lieutenant governor were each elected to a two-year term and were then required to not hold the office for four years before being eligible for election again.  The General Assembly was comprised of two branches, the House of Representatives and the Senate. Both bodies were elected by popular vote.  Members of the House of Representatives served two-year terms. There were a total of 124 members whose districts were determined by a combination of population and the amount of taxes generated. It was through electoral innovations like this that the lowcountry region maintained its political dominance even though it possessed a minority of the state’s white population.  Senators were elected to four year terms.</p>
            <p>The most significant political issue in the state during this period was balancing the interests of the lowcountry and the backcountry.  Under the Constitution of 1790, the state capital was moved from Charleston, on the coast, to Columbia in the interior.  Eventually, the lowcountry representatives agreed to other Constitutional amendments which increased the number of electoral districts in the backcountry region and led to a greater balance of political power.</p>
            <p>The Federalist Party dominated South Carolina in the 1790s as it could count a number of prominent lowcountry planters among their ranks. Many South Carolinians played important roles for the Federalist Party at the national level. The Jeffersonian-Republicans, however, were rising in prominence, especially as Charles Pinckney and Pierce Butler, both of whom signed the Constitution for South Carolina, joined the rival party. Although the Federalists dominated the state until 1800, by 1804 there were no Federalists in power. South Carolina would remain a one-party state until the start of the Civil War.</p>
            <p>The Constitution of 1790 eliminated the religious qualification for voting and holding political office in South Carolina. All free, white men who were 21 years of age, had lived in the state for two years, was a resident of the district in which he was voting, owned fifty acres of land or a town lot and paid taxes were eligible to vote. In 1810 an amendment to the state constitution eliminated the property qualification for voting, extending suffrage to all white men who had lived in the state for six months.  Thus, South Carolina was among the very first states to allow universal white male suffrage.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>James Banner <title>“The Problem of South Carolina”</title> in Stanley Elkins and Eric McKittrick, <title>The Hofstadter Aegis: A Memorial.</title> (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1974) 60-93.</li>
                <li>Walter Edgar, <title>South Carolina: A History</title> (Columbia: University of South Carolina Press, 1998)</li>
                <li>Lacy K. Ford, <title>The Origins of Southern Radicalism: The South Carolina Upcountry, 1800-1860</title> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991)</li>
                <li>Rachel Klein, <title>Unification of a Slave State: The Rise of the Planter Class in the South Carolina Backcountry, 1760-1808</title> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1990).</li>
                <li>George C. Rogers, <title>Evolution of a Federalist: William Loughton Smith of Charleston</title>, (Columbia, SC: University of South Carolina Press, 1962).</li>
                <li>C. Blease Graham, <a href="http://www.cas.sc.edu/poli/courses/scgov/Articles/SC_Constitution_History.htm">South Carolina’s Constitutions</a></li>
                <li>South Carolina Information Highway – <a href="http://www.sciway.net/hist/governors/">Governors</a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Tennessee">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Kristofer Ray<br/>
                Ashland University
            </div>       
            <p>The state of Tennessee originally was the western district of North Carolina. It formally separated from the mother state in 1790, at which time it became the federal Territory South of the River Ohio. In 1795 territorial Governor William Blount called for a constitutional convention, and on February 6, 1796, the convention unanimously approved a document and submitted it to the government in Philadelphia. The House of Representatives subsequently supported Tennessee's bid for statehood, but Senate Federalists disliked the constitution for a number of reasons. A conference committee managed to resolve major differences, however, and Congress formally recognized the state of Tennessee in May 1796.</p>
            <p>The 1796 constitution comprised eleven articles, the eleventh being a declaration of rights that included free navigation of the Mississippi River. Both the executive and the judiciary were firmly under the control of the bicameral General Assembly. In terms of democratic practices, the constitution gave the right to vote to all freemen over twenty-one and did not impose any explicit racial restrictions, which meant that Tennessee's miniscule but growing free black population had the franchise as well. The constitution also provided for a written ballot and apportioned representation on the basis of taxable inhabitants. Elections for both governor and the General Assembly were held once every two years.</p>
            <p>Tennessee was universally Jeffersonian by 1796, but that fact masks significant political complexity. During Tennessee's territorial phase, a small clique of surveyors and speculators had controlled government institutions. They used land accumulation to establish themselves, and they maintained political control because no formal mechanism existed for ordinary settlers to undermine their authority. At the turn of the nineteenth century, however, a burst of militia elections gave ordinary Tennesseans access to positions of community importance. These elections also established a precedent for political opposition. Soon the elite had to construct broad constituencies in an increasingly vibrant popular democracy.</p>
            <p>This shifting political culture coincided with remarkable economic and demographic development, particularly in the region surrounding Nashville. Between 1796 and 1801 the population there grew 200 percent, and by 1815 many of the 292,590 residents were committed to cotton and tobacco cultivation. Commercial agriculture in turn created a mercantile class that integrated "Middle" Tennessee into a global economy. Yet competition associated with this economy created unforeseen popular divisions. Even as planting and merchant interests looked to the government to expedite commercial growth, ordinary farmers believed that limited land accessibility and excessive debt threatened their stability. They therefore used the political sphere to contest more expansive definitions of progress. These debates helped establish "party" interests out of the universal Jeffersonian political culture, and such divisions were solidified through the panic of 1819.</p>
            <p>Middle Tennessee's development stood in sharp contrast to that of the eastern district, which was bounded by the Appalachian Mountains in the east and Cumberland Plateau in the west, and where the soil was generally too poor for significant commercial farming. The region's more self-contained existence made for less dynamic economic development between 1787 and 1825, an issue noted by early nineteenth-century leaders of both regions.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Abernethy, Thomas Perkins. <title>From Frontier to Plantation in Tennessee: A Study in Frontier Democracy.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1932.</li>
                <li>Cumfer, Cynthia. <title>Separate Peoples, One Land: The Minds of Cherokees, Blacks and Whites on the Tennessee Frontier.</title> Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2007.</li>
                <li>Finger, John R. <title>Tennessee Frontiers: Three Regions in Transition.</title> Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2001.</li>
                <li>Ray, Kristofer. <title>Middle Tennessee, 1775–1825: Progress and Popular Democracy on the Southwestern Frontier.</title> Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 2007.</li>
                <li>Remini, Robert. <title>Andrew Jackson and the Course of American Empire, 1767–1821.</title> New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1977.</li>  
                <li><a href="http://www.tennesseeencyclopedia.net">The Tennessee Encyclopedia of History and Culture</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=tdh">Tennessee Documentary History 1796-1850</a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Vermont">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by Kenneth A. Degree
            </div>    
            <p>Vermont became the fourteenth state in 1791, fourteen years after declaring itself independent from the claims of New York. Vermont adopted its first constitution in 1777. Patterning its constitution after the radical document created by Pennsylvania, Vermont went even further, granting universal male suffrage and prohibiting slavery. Wary of power, the framers denied the veto to the governor and forced him to share executive duties with a twelve-man council. A unicameral assembly held legislative power.</p>
            <p>The governor, lieutenant governor, and treasurer were chosen annually in general elections; they needed a majority to gain office. If there was no majority, the winner was chosen by the Joint Assembly (the House, or General Assembly, and the Executive Council). Freemen of each town selected their representative to the General Assembly annually. Members of the Executive Council were elected statewide. United States congressmen were voted on by district, with the exception of the years 1812–1820, when they were chosen statewide. United States senators were chosen by the Joint Assembly. The Council of Censors were the caretakers of the state constitution. Thirteen men, each elected statewide every seven years to a one-year term, were charged with examining legislation for constitutionality and with proposing appropriate amendments. The early years of statehood saw the old political factions of the Arlington Junto (Thomas Chittenden, the Allen brothers, and their followers) and their opponents fade as the Federalist and Democratic-Republican divisions took center stage. Voter participation was initially sparse but inched upward. It took Jefferson's embargo to jolt Vermonters out of their political inertia. Fifty percent more voters cast ballots for governor in 1808 than in 1807. Madison's declaration of war precipitated a similar rise in 1812. The war years contributed the highest voter turnout of the period. The two parties were evenly matched. In the years of 1813 and 1814, their candidates for governor were separated by less than 300 votes, and the parties in the General Assembly were separated by a handful of votes. Vermont's congressmen were elected by the same narrow margins.</p>
            <p>Despite such intense party competition, very few men held statewide office. Straying from its Pennsylvania model, Vermont allowed unlimited reelection to state office and multiple office holding. From 1787 to 1825, only eight men sat in the governor's chair. Only seven men served as lieutenant governor. Just two had been elected treasurer. From 1778 to 1825, only 114 different men sat on the Executive Council, out of a possible 588 seats. Because of this, and because of their ability to hold other offices, a small group were able to wield immense influence in the state.</p>
            <p>After the end of the war, the Federalist Party slowly dissolved, and with it voter participation. The last Federalist candidate for governor ran in 1817. The two-party system being defunct, Republican statewide candidates were chosen by caucus in the legislature and ran virtually unopposed. With no issues to divide the populace, by 1825 the number of votes for governor had dwindled to its lowest level since 1800. </p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Aichele, Gary. <title>"Making the Vermont Constitution, 1777–1824."</title> In Michael Sherman, ed. A More Perfect Union: Vermont Becomes a State, 1777–1816. Montpelier: Vermont Historical Society, 1991, pp. 2–37.</li>
                <li>Bellesilses, Michael. <title>Revolutionary Outlaws: Ethan Allen and the Struggle for Independence on the Early American Frontier.</title> Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1993.</li>
                <li>Brynn, Edward. <title>"Patterns of Dissent: Vermont's Opposition to the War of 1812."</title> Vermont History, 40 (Winter 1972): 10–27.</li>
                <li>Carroll, Daniel P. <title>"Development of the Unicameral Legislature of Vermont."</title> Proceedings of the Vermont Historical Society, III (1932): 12–31.</li>
                <li>Crockett, Walter Hill. <title>Vermont, The Green Mountain State. 5 vols.</title> New York: The Century History Company, 1921–1923.</li>
                <li>Gilles, Paul S. and D. Gregory Sanford, eds. <title>Records of the Council of Censors of the State of Vermont.</title> Montpelier: Secretary of State, 1991.</li>
                <li>Graffagnino, J. Kevin. <title>"’I saw ruin all around’ and ‘A comical spot you may depend’: Orcamus C. Merrill, Rollin C. Mallory, and the Disputed Congressional Election of 1818."</title> Vermont History, 49 (Summer 1981): 159–168.</li>
                <li>Muller, H. Nicholas III. <title>"Early Vermont State Government: Oligarchy or Democracy? 1778–1815."</title> In Reginald L. Cook, ed., Growth and Development of Government in Vermont. The Vermont Academy of Arts and Sciences, Occasional Paper 5 (1970): 5–10.</li>
                <li>________. <title>"Smuggling into Canada: How the Champlain Valley Defied Jefferson's Embargo."</title> Vermont History, 38 (Winter 1970): 5–21.</li>
                <li>Potash, P. Jeffrey. <title>Vermont's Burned-Over District: Patterns of Community Development and Religious Activity, 1761–1850.</title> Brooklyn: Carlson Publishing, 1991.</li>
                <li>Roth, Randolph A. <title>The Democratic Dilemma: Religion, Reform and the Social Order in the Connecticut River Valley of Vermont, 1791–1850.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1987.</li>
                <li>Shaeffer, John N. <title>"A Comparison of the First Constitutions of Vermont and Pennsylvania."</title> Vermont History, 43 (Winter 1975): 33–43.</li>
                <li>Shalhope, Robert E. <title>Bennington and the Green Mountain Boys: The Emergence of Liberal Democracy in Vermont, 1760–1850.</title> Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1996).</li>
                <li>Sherman, Michael, Gene Sessions, and P. Jeffrey Potash. <title>Freedom and Unity: A History of Vermont.</title> Barre, VT: Vermont Historical Society, 2004.</li>
                <li>Smith, Donald Allen. <title>"Green Mountain Insurgency: Transformation of New York's Forty-Year Land War."</title> Vermont History, 64 (Fall 1996): 197–235.</li>
                <li>Walton, Eliakim P., ed. <title>Records of the Governor and Council of the State of Vermont. 8 vols.</title> Montpelier: J. and J. M. Poland, 1873–1880).</li>
                <li>Williamson, Chilton. <title>Vermont in Quandary: 1763–1825.</title> Montpelier: Vermont Historical Society, 1949.</li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
    <authority state="Virginia">
        <history>
            <div class="byline">
                Written by William G. Shade<br/>
                Lehigh University
            </div>       
            <p>The Commonwealth of Virginia rebelled from England and created its own constitution in 1776 as an independent state. This document was written primarily by James Mason and was basically a bill of rights rather than a detailed framework of government. When Virginia joined first other colonies, under the Articles of Confederation, and then the United States, under our present Constitution, its government functioned much as it had as a colony. It had a legislature, but that body and the county courts were dominated by an elite of what one historian has called "Gentlemen Freeholders." This colonial gentry was made up of men who had a good deal of land and twenty or more slaves. Yet the right to vote was much more widely enjoyed than in England. Although governors were appointed by the imperial government before the Revolution, there were popular elections for the House of Burgesses.</p>
            <p>Thus colonial Virginians (at least, many of the white landholding men) were used to elections, and these were several-day events that were quite public and rather intensely social. From 1776 until 1850, the government of Virginia continued to function on its original principles, and the Virginia constitution was not significantly changed. Thomas Jefferson early had called for a revision of the constitution of the commonwealth. His most extensive analysis was in “Notes on the State of Virginia,” published in the 1780s. Most historians are also familiar with a well-known letter written just a year before his death when constitutional reform was being debated. </p>
            <p>The Old Dominion (as Virginia was often called) during the period of the elections being presented here had a governor and his counsel elected by the legislature. The legislature was bicameral, and both houses were popularly elected by the freeholders—essentially white men who held a respectable amount of land or, after the legislature changed the law in 1785, lived in town and owned a house. </p>
            <p>In the 1820s the movement for reform grew. There were a number of demands to democratize the government, by electing the governor popularly, for example, or by building a hierarchy of republics from the local level up (Jefferson’s favorite idea). Even so, the famous collection of prominent Virginian statesmen, including ex-presidents, senators, congressmen and even the chief justice of the Supreme Court of the United States, made very little change in the suffrage, admitting only "householders." The governor's council was eliminated, but the number of elective offices was not expanded. The unequal system of representation in the legislature was addressed by a compromise giving more seats to the west—mostly the Shenandoah Valley—without creating a rational plan for the future.</p>
            <p>During this period, Virginians could vote for their legislators, congressmen, and electors in the presidential elections. They voted yearly in the spring for legislators, every two years for their members of Congress, and every four years for presidential electors. At first they voted for the electors themselves, because they were not willing to say whom they might vote for. The freeholders voted at the polling place closest to their home—a polling place that was often a court house but sometimes a local store. These Virginians voted viva voce, so we have poll books in some counties for some elections to supplement the statistics taken mostly from newspapers.</p>
        </history>
        <bibliography>
            <h3>Bibliography </h3>
            <ul>
                <li>Dabney, Virginius. <title>Virginia: The New Dominion</title> (1971)</li>
                <li>Heinemann, Ronald L., John G. Kolp, Anthony S. Parent Jr., and William G. Shade, <title>Old Dominion, New Commonwealth: A History of Virginia, 1607-2007</title> (2007).</li>
                <li>Salmon, Emily J., and Edward D.C. Campbell, Jr., eds. <title>The Hornbook of Virginia history: A Ready-Reference Guide to the Old Dominion's People, Places, and Past 4th edition.</title> (1994)</li>
                <li><a href="www.state.va.us"> Official State of Virginia Site</a></li> 
                <li><a href="www.lva.lib.va.us"> Library of Virginia </a></li>
                <li><a href="www.vahistorical.org"> Virginia Historical Society</a></li>
            </ul>
        </bibliography>
    </authority>
</div>
