<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<party-authority-list xmlns:xref="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas/xref"
  xmlns:auth="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas/auth">

  <auth:party id="A01" name="Federalist">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

        <p>The Federalist Party</p>

        <p>The Federalist Party was dominated by a man who never actually ran for public office in the United States - Alexander Hamilton.  "Alexander Hamilton was, writes Marcus Cunliffe, 'the executive head with the most urgent program to implement, with the sharpest ideas of what he meant to do and with the boldest desire to shape the national government accordingly.'  In less than two years he presented three reports, defining a federal economic program which forced a major debate not only on the details of the program but on the purpose for which the union has been formed.  Hamilton's own sense of purpose was clear; he would count the revolution for independence a success only if it were followed by the creation of a prosperous commerical nation, comparable, perhaps even competitive, in power and in energy, with its European counterparts." (fn: Marcus Cunliffe, The Nation Takes Shape, 1789-1837, (Chicago, 1959), 23.)  (Linda K. Kerber, History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.  p. 11)</p>

        <p>"Federalists created their political program out of a political vision.  They had shared in the revolutionaries' dream of a Republic of Virtue, and they emerged from a successful war against empire to search for guarantees that the republican experiment would not collapse."  (Kerber, p. 3)</p>

        <p>"The Federalist political demand was for a competent government, one responsible for the destiny of the nation and with the power to direct what that destiny would be.  What was missing in postwar America, they repeatedly complained in a large variety of contexts, was order, predictability, stability.  A competent government would guarantee the prosperity and external security of the nation; a government of countervailing balances was less likely to be threatened by temporary lapses in civic virtue, while remaining strictly accountable to the public will."  (Kerber, p. 4)</p>

        <p>"So long as Federalists controlled and staffed the agencies of the national government, the need to formulate alternate mechanisms for party decision making was veiled; with a Federalist in the White House, Federalists in the Cabinet, and Federalist majorities in Congress, the very institutional agencies of the government would themselves be the mechanism of party.  Federal patronage could be used to bind party workers to the Federalist 'interest.'  'The reason of allowing Congress to appoint its own officers of the Customs, collectors of the taxes and military officers of every rank,' Hamilton said, 'is to create in the interior of each State, a mass of influence in favor of the Federal Government.' (fn: Alexander Hamilton, 1782, quoted in Lisle A. Rose, Prologue to Democracy: The Federalists in the South, 1789-1800, (Lexington, Kentucky, 1968), 3.)  Federalists though of themselves as a government, not as a party; their history in the 1790's would be the history of alignments within the government, rather than of extrernal alignments which sought to influence the machinery of government."  (Kerber, p. 10)</p>

        <p>"Major national issues invigorated the process of party formation; as state groups came, slowly and hesitantly, to resemble each other.  The issues on which pro-administration and anti-administration positions might be assumed increased in number and in obvious significance; the polarity of the parties became clearer."  (Kerber, p. 11)</p>

        <p>"As Adams' presidential decisions sequentially created a definition of the administration's goals as clear as Hamilton's funding program had once done, the range of political ideology which called itself Federalist simply became too broad to the party successfully to cast over it a unifying umbrella.  Federalists were unified in their response to the XYZ Affair, and in their support of the Alien and Sedition Acts, which passed as party measures in the Fifth Congress, but in little else.  The distance between Adams and Hamilton - in political philosophy, in willingness to contemplate war with France, in willingness to manipulate public opinion - was unbridgable; Hamilton's ill-tempered anti-Adams pamphlet of 1800 would be confirmation of a long-established distaste."  (Kerber, p. 14)</p>

        <p>"One result of the war was to add to Federalist strength and party cohesion.  There were several varieties of Federalist congressional opinion on the war: most believed that the Republicans had fomented hard feeling with England so that their party could pose as defende of American honor; many believed that in the aftermath of what they were sure to be an unsuccessful war the Republicans would fall from power and Federalists would be returned to office . . . Regardless of the region from which they came, Federalists voted against the war with virtual unanimity."  (Kerber, p. 24)</p>

        <p>"As an anti-war party, Federalists retained their identity as an opposition well past wartime into a period that is usually known as the Era of Good Feelings and assumed to be the occasion of a one party system.  In 1816, Federalists 'controlled the state governments of Maryland, Delaware, Connecticut and Massachusetts; they cast between forty percent and fifty percent of the popular votes in New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island, New Hampshire and Vermont...Such wide support did not simply vanish...' (fn: Shaw Livermore, Jr.  The Twilight of Federalism: The Disintegration of the Federalist Party 1815-1830, (Princeton, 1962), 265.)  Rather, that support remained available, and people continued to attempt to make careers as Federalists (though, probably fewer initiated new careers as Federalists).  Because men like Rufus King and Harrison Gray Otis retained their partisan identity intact, when real issues surfaced, like the Missouri debates of 1820, a 'formed opposition' still remained to respond to a moral cause and to oppose what they still thought of as a 'Virginia system.'  Each of the candidates, including Jackson in the disputed election of 1824 had Federalist supporters, and their presence made a difference; Shaw Livermore argues that the central 'corrupt bargain' was not Adams' with Clay, but Adams' promise of patronage to Federalists which caused Webster to deliver the crucial Federalist votes that swung the election.  If the war had increased Federalist strength, it also, paradoxically, had operated to decrease it, for prominent Federalists rallied to a beleaguered government in the name of unity and patriotism.  These wartime republicans included no less intense Federalists than Oliver Wolcott of Connecticut and William Plumer of New Hampshire, both of whom went on to become Republican governors of their respective states, and in their careers thus provide emblems for the beginning of a one party period, and the slow breakdown of the first party system."  (Kerber, p. 24)</p>

        <p>"The dreams of the Revolution had been liberty and order, freedom and power; in seeking to make these dreams permanent, to institutionalize some things means to lose others.  The Federalists, the first to be challenged by power, would experience these contradictions most sharply; a party that could include John Adams and Alexander Hamilton, Charles Cotesworth Pinckney and Noah Webster, would be its own oxymoron.  In the end the party perished out of internal contradiction and external rival, but the individuals who staffed it continued on to staff its succesors."  (Kerber, p, 25)</p>

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.</li>
          <li>The Revolution of American Conservatism: The Federalist Party in the Era of Jeffersonian Democracy.  David Hackett Fischer.  New York, 1965, Harper and Row.</li>
          <li>The Age of Federalism: The Early American Republic, 1788-1800.  Stanley Elkins and Eric McKitrick.  New York, 1993, Oxford University Press.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>The Federalists were referred to by many monikers over the years by newspapers.</p>

        <p>American Party:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>In 1809, The Concord Gazette refers to the Federalist Ticket as the American Ticket.</li>
          <li>Beginning in 1810, the Newburyport Herald (MA), began referring to Federalists as the American Party (as opposed to the "French" Party, who were Republicans).  This continued in the 1811 elections.  </li>
        </ul>

        <p>Anti-Republican:</p>

        <p>The Aurora, based in Philadelphia, the most well-known Republican newspaper of the era (see American Aurora: A Democratic-Republican Returns by Richard N. Rosenfeld.) in the February 11, 1800 issue referred to Mr. Holmes, the losing candidate for the Special Election for the Philadelphia County seat in the House of Representatives as an "anti-republican".</p>

        <p>Federal Republican:</p>

        <p>The October 7, 1799 issue of the Maryland Herald (Easton) referred to the Federalist ticket of Talbot County as Federal Republicans.  It would continue to be used intermittently throughout the next 20 years.  Newspapers that used this term included the Gazette of the United States (Philadelphia) and Philadelphia Gazette in 1800, the Newport Mercury in 1808, the New Bedford Mercury in 1810, the True American (Philadelphia) in 1812, the Northumberland Republican (Sunbury) in 1815, the United States Gazette (Philadelphia) in 1816 and the Union (Philadelphia) in 1821 and 1822.</p>

        <p>Friends of Peace / Peace / Peace Ticket:</p>

        <p>Beginning in 1812 ("In laying before our readers the above Canvass of this county, a few remarks become necessary, to refute the Assertion of the war party, that the Friends of Peace are decreasing in this country." Northern Whig (Hudson).  May 11, 1812.) and continuing through to 1815 a number of newspapers referred to the Federalists as the Peace Party (or Peacemaker Party, as the Merrimack Intelligencer (Haverhill) of March 19, 1814 used), as the Peace Ticket or as the Friends of Peace due to their opposition of the War of 1812 (many of these same newspapers referred to the Republicans as the War Party).  This use occurred all through at least August of 1815, with the Raleigh Minerva of August 18, 1815 referring to the Federalist candidates as Peace candidates. </p>

        <p>These newspapers include the Columbian Centinel (Boston), Merrimack Intelligencer (Haverhill), Providence Gazette, the New York Evening Post, the New York Spectator, the Commercial Advertiser (New York), Northern Whig (Hudson), the Broome County Patriot (Chenango Point), the Independent American (Ballston Spa), the Baltimore Patriot, the Alexandria Gazette, Poulson's, Middlesex Gazette (Middletown), the Political and Commercial Register (Philadelphia), Freeman's Journal (Philadelphia), the Carlisle Herald, Northampton Farmer, Intelligencer and Weekly Advertiser (Lancaster), National Intelligencer (Washington), The Federal Republican (New Bern), the Raleigh Minerva, The Star (Raleigh) and Charleston Courier.</p>
        
        <p>The New Hampshire Gazette (Portsmouth) took the opposite side, listing the Federalists in the March 16, 1813 edition as "Advocates of Dishonorable Peace and Submission."</p>
        

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>

        <p>"The Tyranny of Printers": Newspaper Politics in the Early American Republic.  Jeffrey L. Pasley.  Charlottesville, 2001, University Press of Virginia.</p>
      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A02" name="Anti-Federalist">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The Anti-Federalists were never a political party as is thought of in modern times.  It was a coalesced group of voting interests that were united in their opposition to the Constitution.</p>

        <p>"The Antifederal objections to the Constitution fall into four categories.  First, some attacked it for violations of the Whig theory.  Such criticisms came particularly from merchants, lawyers and large landowners who believed in Whig ideology themselves, and represented a sort of right wing, non-agrarian Antifederalism.  Second, almost all of the new plan's opponents accused it of excessive centralization: these were the localists.  Third, some critics attacked the Constitution as leading toward monarchy or aristocracy rather than democracy: these comprised the left wing.  Finally, the agrarians feared that the commerical, creditor, or large propertied interests would benefit at the expense of the farmers."  (Jackson T. Main, History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.  p. 153.)</p>

        <p>"Strictly speaking, Antifederalism ended with the ratification of the Constitution in 1788, without ever producing a party in any modern sense.  During the next few years the term continued as a word of opprobrium, employed by the Federalists to demean whoever opposed the men or policies of the new government.  In some states, opposition nearly ceased.  In others, however, former Antifederalists remained strong and even gained ground, especially where they had developed a local political organization: they composed a majority or a strong minority in such states as New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia, and North Carolina, and appeared elsewhere for the first time, as in New Jersey.  Although they still lacked an inter-state organization and suffered a serious loss of strength during the election of 1788-1789, bitterly fought in certain areas.  Presently, in Congress, they supported amendments and opposed various policies of the Federalists.  The close relationship between the Anti-Federalists and the Jeffersonian Republicans may be traced through a continuity both of men and ideas.  At least seven-eighths of those known to have opposed the Constitution in 1787-1788 became Republicans."  (Main, p. 166)</p>

        <p>"Despite the intensity of Anti-Federalist opposition to the Constitution, no Anti-Constitution party emerged after ratification.  With the demise of the second-convention movement, Anti-Federalists turned their attention to seeking office under the new government.  Federalist efforts to discredit Anti-Federalists turned their attention to seeking office under the new government.  Federalist efforts to discredit Anti-Federalists only diminshed the likelihood of a distinctive Anti-Federalist party's emerging.  Instead, Anti-Federalists set about becoming a loyal opposition.  A number of other factors facilitated this transformation.  The rapid adoption of the Bill of Rights, even if it failed to satisfy many Anti-Federalists, deprived them of an important rallying point.  Reverence for the principles of constitutionalism and a belief that, when properly amended, the new frame of government would effectively protect liberty further weakened the chances of an Anti-Federal's party forming.  The respect accorded George Washington, the new president, also worked against continued opposition.  When coupled with renewed econimic prosperity, all of those factors helped promote the formal demise of Anti-Federalism.  Yet, though Anti-Federalism did not generate an Anti-Constitution party, the term 'Anti-Federalist,' the various texts produced by the Anti-Federalists during ratification, and the alternative constitutional discourses that shaped Anti-Federalism did not simply disappear.  The emergence of a court faction among Federalists caused many former supporters of the Constitution to rehtink the original Anti-Federalist critique.  The efforts of former Federalists, most notable James Madison, and former Anti-Federalists, such as William Findley, were crucial to the creation of a Democratic-Republican opposition.  That loyal opposition drew important ideas and rhetorical themes from Anti-Federalism and adapted them to the exigencies of political conflict in the 1790s."  (p. 170-171)</p>

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>

        <ul>
          <li> History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.  </li>
          <li> The Other Founders: Anti-Federalism and the Dissenting Tradition in America, 1788-1828.  Saul Cornell.  Chapel Hill, 1999, University of North Carolina Press.  </li>
        </ul>

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A03" name="Republican">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>What is today referred to as the Democratic Republican Party did not exist as such under that name.</p>

        <p>"The party name which the Jeffersonians used most commonly in self-designation was Republican.  Since nearly all Americans professed to be supporters of a republic, Federalists were reluctant to allow their opponents the advantage of this name, preferring to label them as Antifederalists, Jacobins, disorganizers, or, at best, Democrats."  (Noble E. Cunningham, Jr., History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.  p. 240.)</p>

        <p>"No precise date can be given for the establishment of the Republican party, for it did not spring suddenly into being, and even those leaders most intimately involved in its formation were not fully aware of what they were creating.  The beginnings of what in course of time became the Republican party can be found in the Second Congress in the congressional faction that contemporaries referred to as the 'republican interest.' . . . An examination of roll calls during the Second Congress indicates that a voting bloc was forming around Madison in opposition to another bloc that united in support of Hamilton's program.  While only about half of the membership of the House could be identified with one or the other of these factions, two such groups had not been observable in the First Congress."  (Cunningham, p. 241)</p>

        <p>"As members of Congress defended their legislative records and sought reelection, they took to the electorate the issues and the disputes that had divided Congress, and they tended in their campaigns for reelection to impart to the voters something of the partisanship that was developing in Congress.  Thus, the party divisions in Congress filtered down to the voters through the electoral process, and voters came to align along the lines that divisions in Congress had marked out.  In this process the congressional factions acquired the mass followings in the county necessary to transform them from capital factions into national political parties."  (Cunningham, p. 244)</p>

        <p>Though Thomas Jefferson was seen as the primary leader of the emerging Republican Party, his retirement in 1793 would force that mantle back upon James Madison.  "Contemporaries referred to 'Madison's party,' and, when Jefferson was put forward for the presidency in 1796, he was recognized as the candidate of Madison's party.  Adams's supporters warned that 'the measures of Madison and Gallatin will be the measures of the executive' if Jefferson were elected.  Under Madison's leadership, the Republican party in Congress moved from a role characterized largely by opposition to administration measures, mostly Hamiltonian inspired, to one of offering policy alternatives and proposing Republican programs."  (Cunningham, p. 246)</p>

        <p>"As the country became dangerously polarized, the Federalists, in 1798 with the passage of the Alien and Sedition Laws, used the full power of the government in an effort to destroy their opponents, whom they saw as subversive.  The Republicans, forced to do battle for their very survival, were compelled to change their strategy radically.  Prior to 1798 they had optimistically believed that the people would repudiate leaders who supported antirepublican measures hostile to the general good of society.  By 1798, however, the Federalists' electoral successes and their hold on the federal government seemed to belie that belief.  Therefore, the Republicans shifted their focus of attention from the national to the state level.  And by emphasizing a more overtly, self-consciously sectional, political enclave strategy, they left the clear implication that state secession and the breakup of the union might follow if the federal government refused to modify its policies and actions to make them more acceptable to opponents, especially Southerners."  (American Politics in the Early Republic: The New Nation in Crisis.  James Roger Sharp.  New Haven, 1993, Yale University Press.  p. 12)</p>

        <p>"On the national level, Republican members of Congress through their informal associations in the national capital formed the basic national party structure.  Many of them lodged together in boarding houses or dined together in small groups where there were ample opportunities to plot party tactics.  They kept in close touch with political leaders and party organizations in their home states.  In 1800, Republican members introduced what was to become the most important element of national party machinery and the most powerful device for the maintenance of congressional influence of the leadership of the party: the congressional nominating caucus."  (Cunningham, p. 252)</p>

        <p>"The coming to power of the Jeffersonians in 1801 marked the beginning of the Republican era that saw the presidency passed from Jefferson to Madison to Monroe.  When the Virginia dynasty came to an end in 1825, the presidential office went to a former Federalist who had become a Republican while Jefferson was president.  But, although John Quincy Adams was a Republican, the presidential election of 1824 shattered the Republican party and destroyed the congressional nominating caucus which had given direction to the party's national structure since 1800.  Adams's presidency was a period of restructuring of parties - a transitional period from the first party system of the Federalists and the Jeffersonians to the second party system of the age of Jackson."  (Cunningham, p. 258-259).</p>

        <p>"During the period from its rise in the 1790's to its breakup in the 1820's, the Jeffersonian Republican party made contributions of major significance to the development of the american political system.  It demonstrated that a political party could be successfully organized in opposition to an administration in power in the national government, win control over that government, and produce orderly changes through the party process.  In challenging the Federalist power, Republicans were innovative in building party machinery, organizing poltical campaigns, employing a party press, and devising campaign techniques to stimulate voter interest in elections and support of republican candidates at the polls.  In the process, it became acceptable for candidates to campaign for office and for their partisans to organize campaign committees, distribute campaign literature, see that voters get to the polls, and adopt other practices which, though subsequently familiar features of american political campaigns, previously had been widely regarded with suspicion and distrust.  Many of the methods of campaigning and the techniques of party organization, introduced by the Jeffersonian Republicans, while falling into disuse by the end of the Republican era, would be revived by the Jacksonians.  In taking office in 1801, the Jeffersonians led the nation through the first transfer of political power in the national government from one party to another; and Jefferson demonstrated that the president could be both the head of his party and the leader of the nation."  (Cunningham, p. 271)</p>

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>
            History of U.S. Political Parties Volume I: 1789-1860: From Factions to Parties.  Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr., ed.  New York, 1973, Chelsea House Publisher.
          </li>
          <li> American Politics in the Early Republic: The New Nation in Crisis.  James Roger Sharp.  New Haven, 1993, Yale University Press.  </li>
          <li> Partisanship and the Birth of America's Second Party, 1796-1800: "Stop the Wheels of Government".  Matthew Q. Dawson.  Westwood, CT, 2000, Greenwood Press.  </li>
          <li> Party of the People: A History of the Democrats.  Jules Witcover.  New York, 2003, Random House </li>
        </ul>

        <p>Beginning in 1799, many Federalist papers began to refer to the Republican Party as Democrats or the Democratic Party.  This continued throughout the first quarter of the 18th Century until what is currently known as the Democratic Party emerged among the followers of Andrew Jackson in the 1828 Presidential Election.</p>

        <p>Republicans were also called by a variety of different terms in various newspapers throughout the period:</p>

        <p>Anti-Federalist:</p>

        <p>Though the Anti-Federalists were not quite the exact same group as the Republicans as they would develop after 1792, there were still some of those who referred to them as such.  The term was used by the following newspapers in the following elections:</p>

        <ul>
          <li> Porcupine's Gazette (Philadelphia).  October 22, 1798.  Pennsylvania 1798 Assembly, Chester County.  </li>
          <li> Virginia Gazette (Richmond).  April 30, 1799.  Virginia 1799 House of Delegates, New Kent County.  </li>
          <li> The Virginia Federalist (Richmond).  April 26, 1800.  Virginia 1800 House of Delegates, Norfolk County.  </li>
          <li> Virginia Gazette (Richmond).  May 12, 1802.  Virginia 1802 House of Delegates, Bedford County.  </li>
          <li> Virginia Gazette (Richmond).  May 12, 1802.  Virginia 1802 House of Delegates, Pittsylvania County.  </li>
          <li> The Salem Gazette.  May 17, 1805.  Massachusetts 1805 House of Representatives, Salem.  </li>
        </ul>

        <p>Democratic Republican:</p>

        <p>Though the term is commonly used today to distinguish the Jeffersonian Republicans from the later Republican Party and because so many of those among the Jeffersonian Republicans eventually became Jacksonian Democrats, this term was extremely rare during the actual period.  It was used by the Readinger Adler in the October 27, 1818 edition recording the 1818 county elections in Pennsylvania.</p>

        <p>French  /  War  /  Warhawk  /  Jacobin:  </p>

        <p>Starting in 1798, various Federalist newspapers would refer to Republicans as Jacobins.  ("In Newbern district the contest lay between two federalists -- No Jacobin had the effrontery to offer himself."  United States Gazette.  September 1, 1798.)  These references continued through until at least 1810.  ("From the Cooperstown Federalist: The election in this County has terminated in favor of the Jacobin Ticket for Assembly.  An important revolution has been effected by the most shameful artifices.  Never before were the jacobin ranks so completely formed and thoroughly drilled for action.  We hope next week to be able to lay before our readers a correct statement of votes, and to exhibit to the world a picture of depravity in the conduct of some of the inspectors of the election which has no parallel."  The American (Herkimer).  May 3, 1810.)</p>

        <p>Beginning in 1810, the Newburyport Herald (MA), began referring to Republicans as the French Party (as opposed to the "American" Party, who were Federalists).  This continued in the 1811 elections.</p>

        <p>Beginning in 1812 ("In laying before our readers the above Canvass of this county, a few remarks become necessary, to refute the Assertion of the war party, that the Friends of Peace are decreasing in this country." Northern Whig (Hudson).  May 11, 1812.) and continuing through 1813 and 1814 a number of newspapers were referring to the Republicans as the War Party (or Warhawk Party, as the Merrimack Intelligencer (Haverhill) of March 19, 1814 used) due to their support of the Madison administration and the War of 1812 (most of these same papers referred to the Federalists as the Peace Party).  These newspapers include the Trenton Federalist, the Columbian Centinel (Boston), the Northern Whig (Hudson), the Independent American (Ballston Spa), the Broome County Patriot (Chenango Point), the New York Spectator, the Commercial Advertiser (New York), the New York Evening Post, the Albany Gazette, the Political and Commercial Register (Philadelphia), the Merrimack Intelligencer (Haverhill), The Federal Republican (New Bern), the Freeman's Journal (Philadelphia), Alexandria Gazette, Poulson's, Middlesex Gazette (Middletown), the Raleigh Minerva and The Star (Raleigh).</p>

        <p>Jackson  /  Jacksonian:</p>

        <p>With the Presidential election of 1824 split among four candidates who were, ostensibly, members of the same political party, the divisions among the Republican Party began to be apparent.</p>

        <p>The phrase "Jackson" or "Jacksonian" candidate was used in nearly every state election in Georgia in 1824 to distinguish between those were were supporters of Andrew Jackson as opposed to the supporters of William H. Crawford.  The Maryland Republican (Annapolis) and the Federal Gazette (Baltimore) used the term "Jacksonian" in the Cecil County elections of 1824 (as opposed to "Adamite" or "Crawfordite") and the Allegheny and Butler county election in Pennsylvania in 1824.</p>
        
        <p>Whig:</p>
        
        <p>The New Hampshire Gazette of March 5, 1816 would refer to the Republican ticket as the Whig Ticket and as being in favor of Peace and Commerce.</p>
        

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A04" name="Quid">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The Quids</p>

        <p>In Pennsylvania, the Quids, known first as "Constitutionalists", arose out of a split among the Republicans in local Philadelphia politics.</p>
        
        <p>The various Republican splinter movements in New York [Burrites, Lewisites and Clintonians] although most had underlying economic and reform issues, they often instead rallied around a central personality. As did most Republican splinter movements in Pennsylvania with exception of the Constitutional Republicans, a movement formed to prevent proposed judicial changes to the Pennsylvania Constitution.  In addition to these, there were within Congress a group of individuals who were often classified as Quids.  Among this group were congressmen from Virginia, Maryland, Kentucky, New Jersey and North Carolina. Mainly elected in 1804 and 1806 as Republicans, they began to question some actions and direction of their party.  When reaction to the Embargo revitalized the Federalist; New York and Pennsylvania dissident Republican movements moved back into the main party. On the Congressional level, a few remained in opposition, some declined to run for re-election, and others were not re-nominated.</p>

        <p>"The first evidence of this appeared in reports of a dinner of the 'Democratic Constitutional Republicans' held at the White Horse Tavern in Philadelphia on March 4, 1805, to celebrate Jefferson's second inauguration.  A few days later the Freeman's Journal printed a proposal, dated March 14, for forming 'The Society of Constitutional Republicans.'  This document recognized the sovereignity of the people, the principle of majority rule, and the right of the people, to alter and abolish their government as they saw fit.  However, it described the Pennsylvania Constitution, along with the Federal Constitution, as 'the noblest invention of human wisdom, for the self-government of man' and avowed that it should be changed only when the motives and causes were 'obvious, cogent, general and conclusive.'  Great political blessings were enjoyed under the Constitution, and it required no alteration.  The list of the society's principles closed with an assertion of loyalty to the existing State and Federal administrations."  (The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Sanford W. Higginbotham.  1952.  p 82-83)</p>

        <p>"Continuing the practice of the preceding year, the Aurora referred to the Constitutional Republicans as Quids.  The latter professed to find the title an honorable one.  A writer on the Freeman's Journal asserted that a 'tertium quid' was a substance used in pharmacy to transform a poison into a medicine and avowed that there was a great need for such an element in politics.  A third party would determine whether there would be 'liberty of despotism.'"  (Higginbotham, p 91)</p>

        <p>"The incident [the Special election of State Senator for District 1 in December of 1805] highlighted one aspect of the dilemma which faced the Pennsylvania Quids so long as they existed - how to avoid becoming a tail to the Federalist kite when the Democratic leaders would not permit them to rejoin their old party."  (Higginbotham, p 105)</p>

        <p>"With McKean ineligible for another term in 1808 and with national issues making union with the Federalists less and less palatable, the great majority of Constitutional Republicans wished to return to the Republican ranks.  However, they had no desire to submit to the leadership of Leib and Duane after the many indignities they had suffered at their hands.  An alliance with the country Republicans, who were also seeking to rid the party of the domination of Leib and Duane, seemed a logical and natural arrangement."  (Higginbotham, p 138)</p>

        <p>"The election of 1808 was a significant demonstration of the depth and strength of Pennsylvania Republicanism.  The Federalists had been favored by many circumstances - Republican disunity over presidential candidates; the Leib-Boileau quarrel among the Democrats; Quid cooperation with them in the three preceding elections; and, most important, the economic hardships of the embargo.  Yet they had lost by an overwhelming majority.  Republican unity reappeared under the stimulus of a revived Federalism campaigning on national issues.  Internal divisions were suppressed, and the Republicans gave undivided support to Madison and Snyder.  The stresses of the campaign destroyed the Constitutional Republicans as a third party, though there were vestiges in a few counties."  (Higginbotham, p 176)</p>

        <p>"The strength and nature of this factionalism varied, but it never entirely disappeared.  The first stage lasted from 1800 to 1805.  Personal and local differences appeared almost immediately as the Federalists virtually abandoned politics.  The struggle between Governor McKean and the country Democrats in the legislature over judicial reform and the failure of the attack on the judiciary culminated in the movement for a constitutional convention.  Duane and Leib, whose arbitrary control of the party in Philadelphia had produced a violent schism, took sides against the Governor.  Aided by the Federalists, the Constitutional Republicans, generally called Quids, were able to defeat the project for a convention and to re-elect McKean."  (Higginbotham, p 328)</p>

        <p>"Adapted from <em>tertium quid</em>, a 'third something,' the name 'Quid' was first prominently used in a political sense in Pennsylvania in 1804, and it was soon affixed to a faction of the Republican party officially calling itself the Society of Constitutional Republicans.  The Pennsylvania Quids attracted Federalist support and in 1805 re-elected Governor Thomas McKean, who had been the choice of a united Republican party in 1802 but was opposed by the majority wing of the party in 1805. (fn: Sanford W. Higginbotham.  The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816, p. 69, 346.)."  ("Who Were the Quids?"  Noble E. Cunningham, Jr.  The Mississippi Valley Historical Review.  Vol. 50, No. 2 (Sep. 1963), p. 254)</p>

        <p>"The use of 'Quid' to refer to various third-party factions which plagued the Jeffersonian Republicans must not, however, be construed to mean that all Quids were part of the same third-party movement.  When John Randolph referred to <em>the</em> third party, he was not being accurate.  There was no such thing.  The Quids in Pennsylvania and in New York - the only states where they represented organized factions - were neither in league with each other nor supporters of Randolph.  In both states, the Republican divisions were the products of local controversies over men, offices, and state policies, and the Quid factions had not direct connection with the schism produced in national politics by Randolph's defection."  (Cunningham, p 255)</p>

        <p>"The opponents of the Philadelphia Democrats and their rural allies were called at various times the Rising Sun Party (after a tavern where they first met in 1802), the Third Party, the Tertium Quids (Third Whats), and more often simply the Quids.  The Quids hoped to tame popular politics by discrediting the radicalism that they blamed on the Philadelphia Democrats.  To do so, they emphasized the nation's future greatness and the prosperity each citizen would enjoy in a vibrant economy with a peaceful representative politics committed to promoting internal economic development.  Accepting, even welcoming, democracy in Pennsylvania, the Quids attempted to redefine the term.  Popular politics would remain the instrument the citizens used to create the conditions that produced material independence.  But democracy would only provide such indepedence of circumstances when Pensylvanians realized that their power should not be used to disrupt or hindred private energies or the use of property."  (Crucible of American Democracy: The Struggle to Fuse Egalitarianism and Capitalism in Jeffersonian Pennsylvania.  Andrew Shankman.  University Press of Kansas.  2004.  p. 96)</p>

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>

        <ul>
          <li> The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Sanford W. Higginbotham.  1952.  </li>
          <li> Crucible of American Democracy: The Struggle to Fuse Egalitarianism and Capitalism in Jeffersonian Pennsylvania.  Andrew Shankman.  University Press of Kansas.  2004.  </li>
        </ul>

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>


  <auth:party id="A05" name="Clintonian">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>The followers of DeWitt Clinton (1769-1828, Governor of New York 1817-1822, 1825-1828), the Clintonians had a life that outlived any other "candidate party" other than the "Jeffersonians" (Republicans) and "Jacksonians" (Democrats).  The term first came to use in the 1806 State Assembly elections in New York.  "Within New York Republicanism, factional battles developed - first between the Clintonians and Burrites, and then between the Clintonians and Lewisites.  In each struggle, Clinton's foes allied with Federalists, and in each the banking power of the Clintonians, exercised through the Manhattan Company, appeared critical to success, emphasizing the ties between Clinton and 'opulent men.'  In 1807, Clinton compensated for his increasing distance from the farmers and mechanics who made up the mass of New York voters by backing Daniel D. Tompkins, 'the farmer's boy,' for governor.  This step created a Republican alternative to which New York City mechanics and upstate farmers might look for Republican leadership - and an alternative with whom Southerners might ally."  (De Witt Clinton and the Rise of the People's Men.  Craig Hanyan with Mary L. Hanyan.  Montreal, 1996, McGill-Queen's University Press.  p. 8)  The term found widespread use outside of New York state during the presidential election of 1812 as Clinton became a fusion candidate, running against James Madison with the support of dissident Republicans and Federalists who had no firm candidate of their own.  Clinton, after being forced from any political office in 1815, maintained a considerable amount of political power as the primary supporter of the Erie Canal.  In 1824, "heading the ticket offered by the People's Movement, he won in an electoral triumph that captured the governorship and almost two-thirds of the state assembly . . . The People's men of New York State launched the earliest broad-based reform movement of the new republic and won control of a state that had one-sixth of the United States' male population.  Beginning their effort soon after the introduction of a new state constitution in 1822, the reformers came to power pledged to democratize New York's political process.  They accomplished their ends after administering a sharp defeat to the regular Republicans of the State."  (Hanyan, p. 4).</p>
        <p>"During the campaign [of 1812], Clinton won support from Federalists who were discontented with the Madison administration's entry into a war with Britain that was bound to have devastating effects on the commerce of the United States; the country ought to have peace of adequate protection of its maritime trade."  (Hanyan, p 9)</p>
        <p>"The Clinton-[New York Chief Justice]-Spencer alliance held together, but over the next three years the tenuous peace within the New York Republican Party dissolved.  Two elements fully emerged, each hoping to dominate the politics of New York in the name of true republicanism.  Martin Van Buren stood out as the leader of a "Bucktail" opposition that increasingly emphasized the virtue of party regularity, while the Clintonians increasingly emphasized the iniquity of party as a potential vessel of conspiracy and oppression that would enhance the power of government at the expense of social harmony. (fn: Richard Hofstadter, The Idea of a Party System: The Rise of Legitimate Opposition in the United States, 1780-1850, Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1969, 219-23)"  (Hanyan, p 10)</p>

        <p>Additional Sources:</p>
        <ul>
          <li> The Concept of Jacksonian Democracy: New York as a Test Case.  Lee Benson.  Atheneum.  New York.  1967.  </li>
          <li> De Witt Clinton and the Rise of the People's Men.  Craig Hanyan with Mary L. Hanyan.  McGill-Queen's University Press.  Montreal and Kingston.  1996.  </li>
          <li> The Birth of Empire: DeWitt Clinton and the American Experience, 1769-1828.  Evan Cornog.  New York, Oxford University Press, 1998.  </li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A06" name="Bucktail">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>Also referred to as the Anti-Clintonians, the Bucktails, lead by Martin Van Buren, became a potent political force in New York arising in the Hudson River Valley in the late 1810's and early 1820's.  The Bucktails would coalesce around the candidacy of William Crawford as a presidential candidate in 1824.</p>

        <p>"The Clinton-[New York Chief Justice]-Spencer alliance held together, but over the next three years the tenuous peace within the New York Republican Party dissolved.  Two elements fully emerged, each hoping to dominate the politics of New York in the name of true republicanism.  Martin Van Buren stood out as the leader of a "Bucktail" opposition that increasingly emphasized the virtue of party regularity, while the Clintonians increasingly emphasized the iniquity of party as a potential vessel of conspiracy and oppression that would enhance the power of government at the expense of social harmony. (fn: Richard Hofstadter, The Idea of a Party System: The Rise of Legitimate Opposition in the United States, 1780-1850, Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1969, 219-23).</p>
        <p>Against the Bolingbrokean essence of Clintonianism, which centred on the magistrate as the artificer of social and political harmony and of prosperity, the regulars pitted the notion of harmonious party order.  The Van Burenite regulars, the organizing force within Bucktailisim worked to articulate systematic party processes that reached out from three engines of power: the legislative caucus, the junto of managers that became known as the Albany Regency, and the Albany Argus, the newspaper that stood at the centre of an extensive press network.  Commending 'regular nominations' and defining which local nominations were regular, the Bucktail press eroded Clinton's Republican following and ultimately his hold on patronage, including the many judicial office holders whom Ambrose Spencer oversaw."  (Hanyan, p 10-11)</p>


        <p>Additional Sources:</p>
        <ul>
          <li> The Concept of Jacksonian Democracy: New York as a Test Case.  Lee Benson.  Atheneum.  New York.  1967.  </li>
          <li> De Witt Clinton and the Rise of the People's Men.  Craig Hanyan with Mary L. Hanyan.  McGill-Queen's University Press.  Montreal and Kingston.  1996.  </li>
        </ul>

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A07" name="Republican splinter parties">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>See <xref:office id="A03">Republican</xref:office>.  These are elections in which two distinct and separate Republican tickets were run.</p>

        <p>Anti-Caucus:</p>

        <p>New Jersey 1820:  Several newspapers, including the Elizabeth-Town Gazette and the True American (Philadelphia) listed a separate ticket of dissident Republicans for the U.S. House of Representatives race in New Jersey in 1820, referred to as the "Anti-Caucus" ticket.  Nominations for At Large candidates on a state wide level could often cause problems. Rotation of candidates, or lack thereof, from different regions/counties would sometimes cause dissension, and    occasionally regional candidates, often an incumbent who had been dropped from the list, would be set up in opposition.  As the Federalist Party declined, the process of country meetings, conventions and the Legislative caucus to nominate candidates came under increased criticism and with less party competition the idea of a more open and balanced method of selecting candidates was becoming a political issue.</p>

        <p>Adamite  /  Crawford:</p>

        <p>While many tickets would grow up around support for one person (such as Clintonians in New York or Snyderites in Pennsylvania), the affiliations of many candidates in various elections in 1823 and 1824 were based around which candidate for President in 1824 the individual candidate was supporting.  While those supporters of Andrew Jackson would become the mainstream part of the Republican Party as it transitioned into the Democratic Party, there were also the followers of John Quincy Adams, many of whom would soon form the basis for, first the National Republican Party, then its successor, the Whig Party.  The followers of William H. Crawford were also identified, though they never coalesced into any sort of larger organization and mostly existed in Georgia, Crawford's home state, though they found support among the <xref:office id="A06">Bucktails</xref:office> of New York.</p>
        
        <p>Friends of Reform:</p>
        
        <p>In 1820, these were Republican candidates in Pennsylvania, mostly in Bucks County, opposed to the present administration.</p>

        <p>New School / New School Republican / Old School / Old School Democrat / Old School Republican:</p>

        <p>Used in Pennsylvania throughout the 1810's.  They were often in opposition to the Constitutionalists.  (See also: Crucible of American Democracy: The Struggle to Fuse Egalitarianism and Capitalism in Jeffersonian Pennsylvania.  Andrew Shankman.  University Press of Kansas.  2004.)</p>

        <p>Opposition Republican:</p>

        <p>Used in several states over the course of over 20 years.</p>

        <p>"Prior to the election of 1802 there had been minor divisions based largely upon personal jealousies and the quest for offices; and a vague dissatisfaction with the Governor had developed.  A new cause of dissension became prominent in 1803 and 1804 as the legislature began to attempt modifications in the judicial system and to use its powers of impeachment against the judges of the State courts.  McKean's opposition to most of these measures alienated many Republicans; and some of his supporters sought Federalist aid to redress the political balance."  (The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Sanford W. Higginbotham.  1952.  p 49)</p>

        <p>"The election of 1803 found the Republican splits becoming deeper and more widespread.  The quarrel over Federal patronage in Philadelphia nearly reached the point of an open breach, while the Rising Sun movement against Leib gained added strength in Philadelphia County.  In Lancaster some of the State officeholders made an unsuccessful attempt to organize a third party movement in support of McKean.  The Federalists for the most part abandoned active politics, although the dissident Republican factions courted their aid."  (Higginbotham, p 58)</p>
        
        <p>Union:</p>
        
        <p>Used in several states over the course of over 20 years.</p>
        
        <p>In Rhode Island in 1807 and 1808 this was a splinter party formed by a combination of those republicans who were supporters of Governor James Fenner, combined with Federalists.</p>
        
        <p>In New Jersey, for several years, from 1807 through 1822, this was a quasi-merged group between Federalists and Republicans, similar to the Quids in Pennsylvania.</p>

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A08" name="candidate parties">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>With the fading of the Federalist party in many areas and the lack of organized political "parties" in the modern-sense, several candidates for election were often described in terms of their support for a single candidate.</p>

        <p>New York 1806-08:  Morgan Lewis was the Governor of New York from 1804-07.  He was elected in 1804 with the support of DeWitt Clinton, but after their split, those supporters of Lewis would be described as such in many newspapers.</p>

        <p>Pennsylvania 1805, 1811:  With the split in the Republican Party in Pennsylvania in 1805 (See <xref:office id="A04">Quid</xref:office>), those followers of Simon Snyder, the Republican candidate for Governor, were identified as Snyderites in many newspapers.  These included the Political and Commercial Advertiser (Philadelphia) and The True American (Philadelphia).  The True American continued to use this designation in the 1811 elections when Snyder was running for re-election, having been elected in the intervening 1808 Gubernatorial election.</p>
        <p>"A strong and aggressive Federalist Party had contributed much to the Republican victory in Pennsylvania in 1799.  It had forged Republican unity and, by its excesses, had added large numbers to the ranks of its opponents.  After the election of 1800 Federalism in the State declined precipitately; and within two years John Quincy Adams was to describe it as 'so completely palsied, that scarcely a trace of it is to be discovered except in here and there a newspaper edited by New England men.' (ft: John Quincy Adams to Rufus King, October 8, 1802 in Charles R. King (ed.) The Life and Correspondence of Rufus King, 6 vols.  (New York, 1894-1900), IV, 176.)  Gratifying as such a metamorphosis must have been to the Republicans, it was not without its cost.  The virtual disappearance of Federalism weakened the compulsion for unity and gave play to Republican differences on measures and men which by 1802 had resulted in a number of local divisions in the party."  (The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Sanford W. Higginbotham.  1952. p 25)</p>
        <p>"Whatever the true explanation of these intricate political maneuvers, the [1801] senatorial election had disclosed division in the Republican ranks.  The party had begun a new era in its history."  (Higginbotham, p 34)</p>

        <p>Pennsylvania 1808, 1813-14:  Michael Leib was elected in 1808 as a U.S. Senator from Pennsylvania.  In that same year, Thomas Humphreys, a candidate for the Bank Director of the Bank of Philadelphia was described by The True American as "Leib's candidate."  Later, in 1813 and 1814, factions would develop in the Republican Party and many candidates for elections in these two years would be described by The Democratic Press (Philadelphia) as Leibites.</p>

        <p>Much of the division in Pennsylvania, and specifically, Philadelphia politics stemmed from those supporters of Simon Snyder, who was the Speaker of the House, and later Governor, and Michael Leib, whose power over the Republican party lead to the Constitutionalists, those supporters of then governor Thomas McKean, to split away from the Republican Party in Pennsylvania as a whole and form their own party for several years, from 1805-1808.</p>

        <p>"The new era was dominated by two themes.  The first of these was the national issue of supporting the administration's foreign policy, including the War of 1812.  Party lines were sharply drawn, and a strong Federalist minority took an active part in politics.  The second was the bitter feud between the Leib-Duane faction and the followers of Snyder.  This persisted in full rancor throughout the period and was only partially subdued by the compulsion for the Democratic unity exerted by the War of 1812."  (Higginbotham, p 177</p>

        <p>"The second period, which ended with the election of 1808, was characterized by two main questions - whether the Federalist-Quid coalition was to form the basis of a permanent new party; and whether the city Democrats, led by Leib and Duane, or the country Democrats, controlled by the adherents of Snyder, should dominate the party.  The growing importance of foreign relations arising out of American neutrality in the Napoleonic wars settled the first question in the negative and forced the postponement of a decision of the second.  In the face of a resurgent Federalism, Pennsylvania Republicans suppressed their differences and united in a successful support of Snyder, Madison, and the embargo.  Foreign affairs continued to be important for the next three years; but congressional vacillation and the relaxing of Federalist efforts within the State permitted the Snyderites and the Duane-Leib faction, now known as the Old School, to fight out their battle for control of the party.  The Olmsted affair offered the occasion, and for a time it appeared that the Old School might be victorious.  However, its own intemperate violence and political blundering redounded to the benefit of the Governor adn his adherents; and by 1811 Duane had forsworn State politics, and the Old School consisted only of Leib and a few hangers-on.  The Snyderites not only dominated the State as a whole, but, acting through Binns, had achieved supremacy in Philadelphia."  (Higginbotham, p 328-329.</p>

        <p>Pennsylvania 1819 Speaker of the House:  Joseph Lawrence is listed as a Findlayite.  In the same election, Rees Hill is listed as a Binnsman by the American Republican of December 14, 1819 and as a Binnite by the Crawford Weekly Messenger (Meadville) of December 17, 1819.  The Village Record of December 15, 1819 lists Lawrence as an Administration candidate and Hill as an Anti-Administration candidate.</p>

      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>


  <auth:party id="A09" name="one-issue parties">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>In the "Era of Good Feelings", when many candidates were of the same party, specific issues would divide the candidates and the candidates would be described in newspapers in terms of their support or opposition of that issue.  The various one-issue parties include:</p>

        <ul>
          <li> New York 1807 Assembly, Dutchess County: The Division and Anti-Division Tickets. </li>
          <li> New Jersey 1810 Essex County: The Bank Tax Ticket and the Anti-Bank Tax Ticket. </li>
          <li> Pennsylvania 1814 Assembly, Columbia, Northumberland and Union: In 1813, Northumberland County had been divided into three counties: Northumberland, Columbia and Union.  The 1814 Assembly election for the district composed of these three counties split on the division. </li>
          <li> Maryland 1816 House of Delegates, Montgomery County: Moderates and Violents.  Both groups appeared to be Federalists, but were listed in several newspapers as Moderates and Violents (including the Daily National Intelligencer (Washington), Alexandria Herald, Federal Republican (Baltimore) and Federal Gazette (Baltimore).  Throughout the early republic, the Federalist remained incredibly united. One exception was the 1816 Montgomery County election.  Montgomery was among the most Federal counties in Maryland, and as sometimes happens when one party is so dominant, dissension, often in the form of personality conflicts erupt. The exact cause of this split is not yet known, but it is interesting that none of the Delegates chosen in 1815 ran for re-election, although one was a candidate for Congress.  Although all the candidates for Delegates were Federalist, it was stated that Republicans supported those listed as Moderates. Among those listed as Violents was Alexander C. Hanson, owner of the virulent Baltimore Federal Republican, which had recently moved back to Maryland from Georgetown. Although Hanson was not elected to the House of Delegates, he was chosen a few months later to the United States Senate. With his appointment, this conflict seemed to subside. </li>
          <li> New Hampshire 1816 House of Representatives, Portsmouth:  Brickites and Woodites.  Both groups were Republicans but were split on a "law passed for the exclusive erection of brick buildings" (Portsmouth Oracle.  March 16, 1816.) </li>
          <li> Kentucky 1817 and 1818:  George Madison who was elected Governor of Kentucky in August 1816, died very shortly after being inaugurated. He was succeeded by Gabriel Slaughter, who had just been elected as Lieutenant Governor. The new Lieutenant Governor, appointed John Pope, who was considered by many to be an avowed Federalist, to the office of Secretary of State for Kentucky. This caused uproar among the Kentucky Republicans and many of them demanded a new election for Governor and that became a big issue in the state elections of 1817.  It would have required an act of the State Legislature to call for a new election of a Governor, so in the 1817 and 1818 state elections, candidates for the state legislature aligned themselves into those who were in favor of a new election for Governor, and those against a new election for Governor. </li>
          <li> New York 1819 Assembly, Ontario County: The Division and Anti-Division Tickets. </li>
          <li> Illinois and Missouri 1820:  Various elections included tickets there listed as either Pro-Slavery and Anti-Slavery or Restrictionist (anti-slavery) and Anti-Restrictionist or variations of the two tickets running against each other (e.g. Pro-Slavery vs. Restrictionist).  These would come up again in Illinois in 1824.  </li>
          <li> Maryland 1822 and 1823 House of Delegates elections in Anne Arundel County and the 1822 Assembly election in Annapolis City: The Caucus and Anti-Caucus tickets.  With their loss of the State Senate in September 1821, and even more for Delegates in the following month of October, by the next election of 1822, the Federalists in many counties offered only token any opposition. With the upcoming Presidential election, in which a Congressional caucus would be called upon to choose the republican candidate, the system of caucus nominations, both nationally and on the state level was coming under increasing attack. In 1822, several Federalist newspapers, listed some candidates in Annapolis City and Anne Arundel County as Anti-Caucus.  In Annapolis City, Lewis Duvall who had been elected for many years a Republican member to the House of Delegates was not re nominated in 1821. This apparently caused some dissension, as he still received substantial support in both 1821 and 1822.  In Anne Arundel County, two candidates were set up in opposition to the Regular Republican ticket and both were elected. It is interesting to note that almost half of their votes came from the most Federalist district within that county.  It does appear that in both places, much of the support for these candidates was drawn from Federalists. Throughout the states, regularly nominated Republican candidates faced opposition from others within their party, a further reflection of dissatisfaction with the nomination process. </li>
          <li> Kentucky 1822 House of Representatives, Bullitt County, Assembly, Fayette County and Assembly, Franklin and Owen Counties, 1823 Assembly, Fayette County and 1824 Assembly, Madison County: The Relief and Anti-Relief (or Constitutionalist) Tickets.  The Relief and Anti-Relief parties were a reaction to the crisis caused by the national economic downturn [Panic of 1819] and how the state of Kentucky was dealing with the aftermath.</li>
          <li> Maryland 1823 House of Delegates, Washington County: The Jew-Bill Ticket and the No Jew-Bill Ticket.  This was in reference to the bill, eventually passed in 1826, that removed the Christian oath requirement for public office in Maryland.  </li>
          <li> Pennsylvania 1824 Commissioner, Moyamensing Township: The People's ticket and the Family Ticket.  </li>
          <li> Pennsylvania 1824 Commissioner, Southwark District: The 25 Cent ticket and the Quality Ticket.  </li>
          <li> Kentucky 1824 House of Representatives, Bourbon, Fayette, Franklin, Mercer and Washington Counties: The Court Ticket and the Country Ticket.  </li>
          
          
        </ul>
      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

  <auth:party id="A10" name="candidates supported by both major parties">
    <auth:description>
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
        <p>As early as the first Federal elections in 1788, there were candidates, who while alligned with one party or another, was supported in the press by both parties in a particular election.</p>
      </div>
    </auth:description>
  </auth:party>

</party-authority-list>
